<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe discourse of mans transgression [an]d of his rede[mption by Christ, with a particular surueigh of the Romish religion]</title>
            <author>Clement, Francis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1593</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18980</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5399.8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3116</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33142676</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33142676</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28175</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18980)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28175)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1873:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe discourse of mans transgression [an]d of his rede[mption by Christ, with a particular surueigh of the Romish religion]</title>
                  <author>Clement, Francis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 87, [13] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richard F[ield] dwelling in the Blacke Friers, neare Lud[gate],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDXCIII [1593]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [13] at end.</note>
                  <note>Contains notes in ms.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: t.p. stained (bracketed information supplied from STC); volume tightly bound, with loss of text. Best copy available for photographing.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G⁸</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographic references and index.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Bible --  Theology.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Redemption --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:28175:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28175:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28175:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28175:2"/>
            <p>BRIEFE DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Richard Field</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Richard F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>elling in the Blacke Friers, near Lud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> MDXCIII</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:28175:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28175:3"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN Reader, grace and peace in Chriſt Ieſus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen it pleaſed the Lord in a mercifull and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle correction, to lay his fatherly rod of ſickneſſe and mortalitie, in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumne laſt, vpon this Citie of London, the ſchooles there both publike and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, ſoone after (as it vvas requiſite) began to breake-vp. VVhereupon the Teachers vvere generally at more ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to follovv that courſe of practiſe, after the diuerſe ſtudies of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall profeſsions, vvhich euery one affected. Among vvhom my ſelfe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed likevviſe to publish ſomevvhat of my priuate readings (as leyſure gaue
<pb facs="tcp:28175:4"/> leaue) in diuinitie. VVherein this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe I entred the rather for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoofe and benefite of my Scholers, to vvhom (as their young yeares vvere able, and capacities apt to conceiue) I haue vſed to interpret a portion of the nevve Teſtament by the ſpace of an houre euery Saboth in the morning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Common prayer: vvherby I might the better both traine them to * remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12, 1.</note> novv their Creator in the dayes of their youth, and inſtill into their tender minds the vvonderfull conſonancie &amp; concord of many notable ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces vvith the vvord of God, vvhich novve and then met the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their vveekly lectures of <note n="*" place="margin">The ſtudy of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie is a dead, darke, and erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous labor without the knowledge of Diuinitie, wherby it is quickned, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened, &amp; recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and ſo it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth eaſie, pleaſant, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents.</note> humanitie: and vvithall bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in diſliking of other diſcord and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable ſpeeches, vvhich commonly in ſome Poets are vvithout all modeſty. But beſides theſe, the learned vvell knovv vvhat excellent ſayings, most conſonant and conſpiring vvith the
<pb facs="tcp:28175:4"/> vvord of God, are ſcattered in heathen authors Greeke and Latine, vvhich it vvere a great fault in the maiſter ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lightly to ouerpaſſe vvith ſilence, as vnprofitable, or to leaue his ſcholers ignorant of thoſe maruellous lights of Nature, vvhich the Lord had left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Heathen (to the intent that they should be vvithout <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 1, 4.</note> excuſe) euen teſtimonies of his vvill, according to his vvritten vvord, vttered by their ovvne mouthes, hovvſoeuer yet the ſame vvere quickly quenched, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly turned to mere <note n="*" place="margin">Ro. 1, 21. Eph. 4, 17.</note> 
               <hi>mataeologie</hi> and foolish thoughts, through the vanitie of their darke hearts and mindes. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit they had the Shepherds Kalender, or Plovv-mans alphabet of the vvorld, vvherein vvas vvritten in great ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall letters, that euery vnlearned man among them might plainly read <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 1, 19.</note> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) that vvhich may be <note n="*" place="margin">In ſteed of this knowledge of god is publikely prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by an ancient Record the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of God, and that in a ſolemne Altar at Athens, their chiefe Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity of learning &amp; wiſdom, Act. 17, 23. See the cauſe why, Rom. 1. v. 21. 24. 28.</note> known of God, as the Apoſtle vvell noteth to
<pb facs="tcp:28175:5"/> the Romans, vvhich might haue taught them as much in effect, for the true and diſtinct knovvledge of the godhead, as the Lavve, and vvord of God did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the Ievves, Rom. 2, 15. For, by the very ſight of the viſible heauens ouer their heads (declaring the glorious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of the maker, Pſal. 19, 1.) they might euidently ſee, and certainly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne his <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 1, 20.</note> deitie and Godhead: &amp; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviſe his <note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 1, 21.</note> wiſedome, the ſonne of God, <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 136, 5. Prou. 3, 19. and 8, 27. &amp;c. Heb. 1, 2.</note> by vvhom the Lord made heauen and earth, the ſea, and all the creatures in them, the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d perſon in Trinitie. And his <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 1, 20.</note> eternall povver, the holy Ghost, <note n="*" place="margin">Geneſ. 1, 2.</note> mouing and extending ouer all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <note n="*" place="margin">Hebr. 1, 3.</note> ſuſtaining, comforting, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing them, the third perſon alſo in that diuine Trinitie. Albeit (I ſay) they might clearely ſee that this God, that created heauen and earth, the ſea, and all things, that in them are, <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 14, 15. &amp;c.</note> left not him ſelfe vvithout vvitneſſe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb facs="tcp:28175:5"/> them, in that he did them good, <note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 5, 45<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> made his ſunne to ariſe vpon them, and gaue them raine from heauen, and frutefull ſeaſons, filling their hearts vvith food and gladneſſe, <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 17, 25. &amp;c.</note> giuing to all life and breath, and all things: for in him vve liue, and moue, and haue our being, as alſo certaine of their ovvne Poets haue ſayd: yet vvere they ſo far from Dauids thoughts, vpon the vievv of theſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens (vvho in holy meditation confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thus vnto God: <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 8, 3. &amp;c.</note> VVhen I behold thy heauens, euen the vvorks of thy fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, the Moone and the ſtars, vvhich thou haſt ordeined, vvhat is man (think I) that thou art mindfull of him? &amp; the ſon of man that thou viſiteſt him? &amp;c.) that contraryvviſe they <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 32, 9.</note> (like the horſe and mule, vvhich vnderſtand not) <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 1, 25.</note> turned the truth of God vnto a lye, and vvorshipped the creature, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking the Creator, vvhich is bleſſed for euer. And ſo, vvhiles they <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 1, 22. &amp; 1. Cor. 1, 22.</note> profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:28175:6"/> them ſelues to be vviſe, they became ſtarke fooles, as the Apoſtle alſo vvit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth. Theſe heathen, vve haue, in this our Diſcourſe, declared vvho they vvere, vvhat time they vvere ſeuered, hovv long they continued ſeparate from Gods people, and by vvhom, and hovve they vvere called, and reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled to their brethren againe. Of them therfore here vvill I vvrite no more but this: vvhen in the yeare of the vvorld 3577, Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander the great had ſubdued the Medes and Perſians, &amp; many other nations, as vve haue briefly touched in this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, the Greeke tongue, vvhich though 600 years before that time, it vvas ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry famous and florishing, as may ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally appeare by Homers vvorks (for all) the honor both of learning and Nature: yet then chiefly began to be generally ſtudied in all the vvorld, inſomuch that euery nation, as they vvere ſubiect to the Grecians, ſo they coueted chiefly to
<pb facs="tcp:28175:6"/> come in fauour by ſpeaking their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. But after that the Romanes had brought vnder the Grecians, &amp; vvere alſo conquerors of the vvorld, the Latin tongue likevviſe grevv to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all nations, vvhich held on til the coming of Chriſt. VVherfore Pilat (the Lord guiding his vvauering mind and pen, both for the matter &amp; maner) was not content to vvrite Chriſts Title in<note place="margin">Luke 23. 38.</note> Hebrue the Ievves tongue only, but in Greeke and Latine the tongues of the heathen alſo, that ſo it might appeare (though Pilate thought of no ſuch my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie) that aſvvel the Gentiles &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, as the nation of the Ievves, vvere to take notice, &amp; reap benefit of Chriſts death and paſsion. Novv the Theme or purport of my vvriting, I deſired ſuch, as might be both moſt neceſſarie for all ſortes, and leaſt handled of any in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular. VVhich thing in this kinde of ſtudie, &amp; in theſe our days (vvherin
<pb facs="tcp:28175:7"/> mouing and vvorking in vs) conceiue comfortable hope to our vnſpeakeable ioy in the Lord, and thervvithall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to glorifie God, the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, vvho hath called vs out of ignorance, ſinne and error, into his maruellous light: and tranſlated vs into the kingdome of his deare Sonne. To vvhich kingdome the Lord Ieſus, vvho alone hath redeemed vs, conduct and bring vs, by a true and liuely faith in the merites of his death and paſsion, to vvhom, vvith God the Father, and the holy Spirit, be giuen all honour, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, povver and glorie for euer. From my houſe in Turnmill ſtreete the 4 of Noue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, in the yeare of the ioyfull incarnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt our redeemer 1592 and the yeare of the vvorld 5502.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>F. Clement.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:28175:7"/>
            <head>THE CREATION, TRANSGRESSION AND REDEMPTION OF MAN.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>In peruſing this Treatiſe, courteous Reader (I pray you) take the Bible, and turne to euery place here quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which meeteth you in the reading: ſo ſhall you reap double profit of your paines, and greatly confirme your conſcience in the aſſurance of the word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>GOD the Creator</item>
                  <item>MAN y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tranſgreſſor</item>
               </list> Chriſt being
<list>
                  <item>God &amp;</item>
                  <item>Man</item>
               </list> the Redeemer.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lord God, the father, the Sonne, and the holy Spirit, being one, and the ſame god in ſubſtance, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and nature, yet three diſtinct perſons in the ſelf ſame diuine nature: being alſo without beginning, and from all eternitie, at the <note n="a" place="margin">Time began at the creation. The Angels alſo were then created, as ſtately witneſſes of Gods will, for the ſeruice of the elect. Heb. 1. 14.</note> beginning to manifeſt him ſelfe by his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:28175:8"/> workes (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh Rom. 1. verſ. 19. 20.) in ſixe dayes created heauen and earth, the ſea, and all the creatures in them; and laſt of all in the <note n="b" place="margin">Which is out Friday: ſo to the day of mans crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being alſo ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the day of his tranſgreſſion, moſt aptly anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the day of his redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which we commonly call good Friday.</note> ſixt day of the creation, he made man (male and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male) after his owne image and likeneſſe, <note n="c" place="margin">The ſoul of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is a ſpirituall &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine thing, inſpired in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is immortall, Gen. 2. 7. Iob. 33. 4. Eccle. 12. 7. which being ſeparate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bodie, it ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone: but after the general iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t together likewiſe with the body im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, ſhal either reſt in eternal ioy, or abide in endles wo, Ioh. 5. 29.</note> breathing in their faces the breath of life, whereby they became liuing ſoules, Gen. 1. and 2. effectually bleſſing them, and commanding them to multiply, and to ſubdue the earth, to rule ouer the fiſh of the ſea, the foules of heauen, and the beaſts of the field, which came therefore willingly to ſubmit them ſelues to <hi>Adam,</hi> who, as their ſoueraigne, gaue them ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall names, as pleaſed him, Gen. 1, 28. &amp; 2. 19. Pſal. 8, 6. &amp;c. And in Eden or Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, a garden moſt goodly and pleaſant for waters, and all fruteful trees, the Lord God ſet <hi>Adam</hi> and the woman, permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them free libertie to eate of all the trees in Paradiſe, ſaue onely of one tree, whereof he forbad them to eat, moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly telling them, that whenſoeuer they ſhould eate thereof, they ſhould die the <note n="d" place="margin">By Adam ſinne entred into the world, &amp; death by ſin goeth ouer all men, becauſe all men haue ſinned, Rom 5 12: for it is appointed vnto me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they ſhal once die, and then cometh the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Hebr. 9, 27: but they that liue til the laſt day, ſhal in a moment, in ſted of death, be changed from mortall to immortall. 1. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5. ver. 52. 53.</note> death. Gen. 2. 8. &amp;c. and 3. 2. &amp;c. Thus
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:28175:8"/> 
               <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eua</hi> our firſt parentes being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reated right perfect, and moſt innocent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ully furniſhed with all goodly gallant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe of bodie, and heauenly ornaments <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the mind, bearing all the rule and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eraigntie in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, both of the earth it ſelf, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd of all the creatures therein, Pſal. 8, 4. &amp;c) receiued all theſe moſt excellent and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſtimable iewels at the Lords hand to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir owne keepe and cuſtodie, both for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem ſelues, and for their poſteritie for euermore: hauing alſo free-will and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie in them ſelues, either to ſtand and abide in the perfection of the diuine like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of righteouſneſſe, holineſſe &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowledge, wherein they were made, or to fall therefrom at their owne wil and choiſe: they through the ſubtiltie of the enuious <note n="e" place="margin">Becauſe Moſes had not me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned the creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Angels, nor Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s fal, which was not before the 6. day, as we ſee by that ſuruey, Gen. 1. 31. but either on that day, or very ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after, as Io. 8 44. therefore he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of the ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Satan vnder the name of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, which for his naturall wilineſſe, was a fit inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t both for Satan to deceiue man by, &amp; for Moſes to repre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent vnto the rude Iſraelits, the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall craftineſſe of the Deuill.</note> Serpent the deuil, moſt vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully <note n="f" place="margin">This tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was a moſt grieuous ſin: for he brake not ſimply the Lords co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, but verie confidently credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s lies, which Eue reported vnto him, moſt wickedly grudged at his crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tor, and conceiued an hatefull indignation againſt God, for that he had forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den him the eating of that frute, by eating whereof (as he was wickedly perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) he ſhould be like vnto God, and coequall with his Creator. All this is e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently gathered by Satans perſwaſion, that they ſhould be as gods by tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: &amp; likewiſe of Gods deriding Adams proud preſumption in thinking by his treſpaſſe to become as God him ſelfe, Gen. 3. verſ. 5. 22. And where S. Paule ſaith that Adam was not deceiued, 1. Tim. 2, 14, he ſpeaketh not that either to excuſe, or to extenuate Adams ſin: but onely to admoniſh women of their dulie deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſubiection vnto their husbands, Gen. 3. 16. becauſe their grandmother Eue, being firſt deceiued her ſelfe, through the ſubtilty of the ſerpent, 2. Cor. 11, 3, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came alſo Satans inſtrument to deceiue the man, Gen. 3, 6. Reade Eccleſ. 25, 26.</note> tranſgreſſed the Lords comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:28175:9"/> in eating of the forbidden frute, more beleeuing the lying ſerpent, then their gracious Creator, and ſo wilfully running into the iuſt puniſhment of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall death, due to them ſelues, and to all their poſteritie for the ſame, moſt iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bereft, &amp; depriued for euer both them ſelues &amp; their of-ſpring, of all theſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly ornaments and Lordly preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues. But our gratious and wonderfull louing God moſt mercifully cauſed Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and-cry to be made after theſe wofull wights, to arrouſe ſinfull <hi>Adam</hi> out of the buſhes, whither he had vainely fled to hide himſelf and after conference with him, as well to let him ſee him ſelfe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeleſſe, as to conuince him of moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſſe, at length <note n="g" place="margin">To the end that man might alway remember &amp; feele this diſobedience, the Lord impoſed a curſe vpon the whole courſe of Nature as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mans vſe, Gen. 3, 17: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which the very creature gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnto this pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent to be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Rom 8, 20 &amp;c. which ſhall be by ſire at doomeſday as S. Peter writeth 2. Pet. 3, 7.</note> offreth him this ſpeciall grace (purpoſed in him ſelfe from euerlaſting, whereby the Lord both clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his iuſtice, and ſhewed his mercie,) that the ſeed of the woman ſhould bruſe the ſerpents head, Gen. 3, 15. <hi>Adam</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued this ſhort ſentence, and through faith in this promiſe was ſaued. In the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of this promiſe were all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and faithfull, before <hi>Noahs</hi> flood
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:28175:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſaued. The floud came in the yeare of the world 1656. For notwithſtanding the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie exerciſes which the Lord had enioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Adam</hi> &amp; his ofſpring to practiſe by offrings &amp; ſacrifices, as types &amp; patterns of that promiſed ſeede Chriſt, the lambe of God, which therefore in purpoſe of God, in promiſe to man, and in type of <note n="h" place="margin">It is verie like that the skins of thoſe beaſtes, which were ſlaine for ſacrifice at that inſtant of the promiſe of rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſerued to cloth Adams na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 3, 21 that as their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies were burnt in ſacrifice to prefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure Adams deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance from hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire: ſo their hides likewiſe might hide his ſhame, keepe his bodie from cold, and continuallie put him in mind of the Lords mercifull couenant. And thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the Lord in commaunding the Iſraelites to weare that blew gard, as a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of his lawes, in the borders of their garmentes, Num. 15 verſ 38. 39. but the apparel of chriſtians is the Lord Ieſus Chriſt &amp; his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertues as faith, righteouſneſſe, holineſſe of life, &amp;c. Rom. 13, 14. Gal. 3; 27. Eph. 4, 24. which in the parable are called the wedding garm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt, Mat. 22, 11. read Reuelat. 3. verſ. 4. 18, &amp; 14, 5.</note> ſacrifice was ſlaine from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world, Reu. 13, 8. as we plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſee by <hi>Adams</hi> ſonnes offrings. Gen. 4. verſ. 3. 4. Which were doubtles according to Gods owne appointment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted onlie by faith, Hebr. 11, 4. And were alſo the faithfull <note n="i" place="margin">The firſt borne in euerie familie, till the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aw was the ſacrificer: but as the law the Leuites were appointed thervnto, Exo. 19, 22 &amp; 24, 5. Num. 8. verſ. 18. 19. whoſe offrings (as is verie like) were approued by ſite ſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen to conſume their ſacrifices, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare theſe quotations, Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 4. Leu. 9, 24. 1 King. 18, 38. 1 Chr. 21, 26. 2 Chr. 7, 1 Hebr. 11, 4.</note> practiſes of all the ten fathers before the floud, as we may well perceiue by this, that the Lord reuealed to them what beaſts &amp; fowls were clean, &amp; what vncleane, Gen. 7, 2. and 8, 20. As likewiſe after the floud, and before the law, the example of <hi>Noah,</hi> Geneſ. 8, 20.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:28175:10"/> 
               <hi>Melchi-zedek,</hi> Geneſ. 14, 18. <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 12, verſ. 7. 8. &amp; 13, 18. <hi>Iſaak</hi> Gen. 26, 25. <hi>Iaacob,</hi> Gen. 31, 54. and of <hi>Iob, Iob,</hi> 1, 5. &amp; 42. verſ. 8. 9. witneſſeth. And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding alſo thoſe reuerent &amp; ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſagies, the ten <note n="k" place="margin">Before Noahs floud they liued with bread, ſalets, rootes, frutes, and all increaſe of the earth &amp;c. Gen. 1. 29. milke, butter, &amp;c. of the flockes or heards, Gene. 4 2. not hauing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement to touch the life of anie creature for meat: but at the floud the Lord ſo weakned the ſtate of mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, in ſhortning his daies, that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtood in neede of fiſh and fleſh alſo to ſuſteine life: for before the floud the eating neither of fiſh nor of fleſh was permitted, Gen. 9, 3.</note> long-liued fathers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Noahs</hi> floud, ſet downe in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by <hi>Moſes,</hi> Gen. 5, 3. &amp;c. Who were all graue prophets, &amp; preachers to proclaime Gods mercies to faithfull penitents, and to denounce his iudgements againſt the ſtubburne ſinners of that age: yet they conuerſing with <hi>Cains</hi> poſteritie (whoſe companie by <hi>Cains</hi> far baniſhment, the Lord would haue had his to auoide, Gen. 4, 14.) were now become moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane and wicked, corrupting the true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and worſhip of God, in ſo much that, at this time of the floud, there was but onelie <hi>Noah,</hi> the tenth father of that age, whom the Lord found faithfull vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the whole earth, Gen. 6, 9. &amp; 7, 1. And although the Lord had warned them ſixe ſcore yeares before of that vniuerſall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge and deſtruction, and that they both heard the continuall admonitions, &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement preachings of theſe three excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:28175:10"/> fathers <hi>Methuſhelah, Lamech,</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> all the time <note n="l" place="margin">The floud came the 17. day of the 2. moneth, Gen. 7. 11. which is our O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctober (as compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Ex. 12, 2. with 23, 16. you may plainlie perceiue) and in the moneth before died Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſhelah, 5. years after the death of Lamech. Noah &amp; his 3. ſonnes, Sem, Ham, &amp; Iapheth, with their 4. wiues Gen. 6. verſ. 10. 18. were thoſe 8. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſaued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the floud in the Arke, 1. Pet. 3, 20. by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſee how the earth is repleniſhed with inhabitants, Gen. 10. &amp; of the caution in Gods decree, 800. years after (counting from the confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of tongues, Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 11, 8.) for the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael to ſucceede Hams poſteritie the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Cananites, Deut. 32, 8. Noah. Sem.</note> almoſt of that long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pace of repentance, and alſo ſaw <hi>Noahs</hi> diligence in preparing the Ark, by Gods commandement, Geneſ 6. verſ. 13. 14. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that dreadfull day: yet ſo wicked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd deſperate they were, that they toke no notice thereof, though it ſtood vppon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he deſtruction both of their bodies and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oules, for they knew nothing of it (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur Sauiour teſtifieth) till the floud came &amp; ſwept them all away, Mat. 24, 39. Some <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ew yeares after the floud, this promiſe was renewed: for <hi>Noah,</hi> as a Prophet, told <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore diſtinctlie of what familie this ſeede <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould come, ſaying: Bleſſed be the Lord God of <hi>Sem,</hi> Geneſ. 9, 26. noting thereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wo things vnto vs, both that this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng ſhould come of the linage of <hi>Sem</hi> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>econd ſonne: and alſo that the reſt of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orld (as heathen idolaters) ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uered from <hi>Sems</hi> familie for a time, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich came to paſſe in the tenth genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on after at <hi>Abrahams</hi> calling from <hi>VR</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Chaldea. <hi>Moſes</hi> recordeth <hi>Sems</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion to abraham, Gen. 11, 10. &amp;c. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am</hi> was borne in the yeare of the world
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:28175:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> 2008, and two yeares after the death of<note place="margin">Abraham.</note> 
               <hi>Noah,</hi> which was 352 yeares after the floud, when now all the families of the earth, (ſauing <hi>Melchi-zedek,</hi> who by all likelihod, was that old <hi>Sem,</hi> Gen. 11. verſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 10. 11. &amp; 14, 18 &amp;c.) were fallen to idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie and atheiſme, euen <hi>Terah</hi> the father of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Ioſh. 24. verſe. 2. 14. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> was 70. yeares old, the Lord <note n="m" place="margin">By three proofs eſpeciallie the ſcriptures co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend Abrahams faith vnto vs: 1. by his willingneſſe in forſaking his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe, kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and countrie, to follow Gods calling he wiſt not whither, Gen. 12, 1. Act. 7. 3 Gal. 3. verſ 6, 17. Hebr. 11, 8. 2. by his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured hope in Gods promiſe to obteine a ſonne, when in reaſon ther was no hope, Rom. 4, 19 &amp;c. 3. by the readie offring vp of his ſon Iſaak, in ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had receiued the promiſes, Heb. 11, 17. &amp;c. In him therefore we ſee a worthie pattern of our faith, Gal. 3, 7.</note> cald him out of <hi>VR</hi> of the Chaldees, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding him to forſake his natiue ſoil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; countrie, and to goe into a land, that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would ſhew him, promiſing moſt amp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to bleſſe him &amp; his. Now more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie renewing and confirming vnto him the promiſe of that holie ſeed, that in him all the families of the earth ſhould be bleſſed, Gen. 12, 1 &amp;c. and 17, 1 &amp;c. Act. 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. which S. <hi>Paul</hi> interpreteth thus: To <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> and his ſeede were the promiſes made: He ſaith not, to the ſeedes, as ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of manie: but, And to thy ſeede, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of one which is Chriſt, Galat. 3, 16. And heare at <hi>Abrahams</hi> calling from among the Idolaters, <note n="n" place="margin">The Iewes ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from the Gentils, when, &amp; how long.</note> beginneth that hateful ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> betweene the church of God, through ceremonies, and the reſidue of the world
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:28175:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> being heathen atheiſts, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake ſometime of the Epheſians, Eph. 2. verſ. 11. 12. which hatred and enemitie continued 1864. yeares, viz. from <hi>Abrahams</hi> calling from <hi>VR</hi> of Chaldea, but chieflie from the birth of his ſonne <hi>Iſaak</hi> which was 30. yeares after through the ſigne of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, Gen. 21. verſ. 4. 5. And much more increaſed 400. yeares after, at <hi>Moſes</hi> law, Exod. 33, 16. Leuit. 20, 26.) vnto the full accompliſhment of this holie ſeede Chriſt, who abrogating through his fleſh the hatred (that is,) the law of cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial commandements, which ſtandeth in ordinances, made of <note n="o" place="margin">The Gentiles were gathered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſhepefold of the Iewes, Pſa. 47. 3. Ioh. 10. 16. by Chriſt the great ſhepheard of the ſheepe, Iſai, 49, 6. Mat. 28. verſ. 18. 19 Heb. 13. 20. that there might be one ſhepefold, &amp; one ſhepheard, &amp; Biſhop of our ſoules, Ezech. 37, 24. 1 Pet. 2, 25.</note> twaine (Iew and Gentile) one new man in himſelfe ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king peace. Epheſ. 2, 14 &amp;c. In regard of which pacification by Chriſt, the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are called the remnant of the brethren, <hi>Micah.</hi> 5, 3. The brethren. Iſa. 66, 20. A ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Cant 8, 8. Sheepe, Ioh. 10, 16. a rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Iſraell, Rom. 11, 26. fellowes with<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Iſraell of Chriſtes miſtical bodie. Eph. 3, 6.</p>
            <p>This promiſe of the bleſſed ſeede the Lord confirmeth alſo to <hi>Iſaak</hi> Gen. 26,<note place="margin">Iſaak. Iacob.</note> 4. likewiſe to <hi>Iacob</hi> Gen. 28, 14. And after the Lord had now 2509. yeares (for ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:28175:12"/> was it from the creation to the law) hel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the faithfull in long ſuſpenſe of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Redeemer, it pleaſed him (vppon his miraculouſlie deliuering his peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out of Egipt, whither, becauſe of <hi>Ioſeph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Law.</note> preferment, Geneſ. 45. 8. <hi>Iacob,</hi> by God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> commaundment, had caried them. Gen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 46, 3 &amp;c.) to ſet downe in his writte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> law, deliuered by <hi>Moſes,</hi> a plaine platform at large of the ſame promiſe ſo often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore renewed. Which law ſhould be both as a hand-writing vnto his people for to ſhew them the grieuouſnes of their tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, Col. 2, 14. til the promiſed ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould come, vnto which the promiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were made, Gal. 3, 19. and their weake vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ableneſſe to attaine to the perfect puriti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of that law, Rom 8, 3 (for it is ſpirituall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but ſinful man is carnal, Rom. 7, 14) And alſo as a child-guide, or tutor to conduc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them to this promiſed ſeed Chriſt, Gal. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 24. which things were moſt liuelie prefi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gured by the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dry waſhings, purifyings offrings and ſacrifices, which they wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bound to obſerue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> aſwell to witneſſe thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> owne vncleanneſſe through <hi>Adams</hi> tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>greſſion, as to imprint before their eies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:28175:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> plaine ſtampe and pattern of Chriſts ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frings, who ſhould fulfil that law for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Mat. 5, 17. Rom. 8, 2 &amp;c. And bearing our ſinnes in his body on the croſſe, 1 Pet. 2, 24. bring in eternall iuſtice for vs all, Dan. 9, 24.</p>
            <p>One conſideration hereof wil I preſent for all, when the Iew, in the time of the law ſhould, behold the harmeleſſe beaſt, that was to be ſlaine for ſacrifice, vppon the head, whereof he was to * put his hands, Leuit. 1, 4. whereby he proteſted<note place="margin">Read 2. Chron. 29. 23.</note> his owne guiltines of death for his ſinnes, which it (as a figure of Chriſt) was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to ſuffer, the verie ſight of ſo wofull a ſpectacle could not but <note n="p" place="margin">The right vſe of the ſacrifices of the law.</note> moue euen his flintie heart to be inwardlie touched with a deepe remorſe &amp; ſorrow for his ſinnes: and, ſo trembling at Gods iudgement, force him (if ther were anie ſparkle of grace) to flee by faith to the truth of that fearefull figure, which was Chriſt, this promiſed redeemer. The ſame promiſe is likewiſe 440. yeares after the law, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed to king <hi>Dauid,</hi> that this bleſſed<note place="margin">Dauid.</note> ſeede ſhould deſcend in kingly raſe from his <note n="q" place="margin">Herehence it is that in the ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> teſtament our Lord is ſo vſuallie called the ſonne of Dauid, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which name, for want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of Chriſtes two natures his God-head &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hod, our Sauiour put the Phariſees to a no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-plus, Mat. 22, 41 &amp;c. for they would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him to be God, though both the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures &amp; his works ſo teſtified, Ioh. 5, 18. &amp; 10, 33. Ioh. 5, 39. Mat. 11. verſ. 3. 4. 5. Ioh. 5. 36 &amp; 15 24.</note> loines, 2 Sam. 7, 12 &amp;c. Pſa. 132, 11.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:28175:13"/> Iſai. 9, 7. The manner of the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof Saint <hi>Luke</hi> penneth thus: And in the ſixt moneth, the Angell <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briel</hi> was ſent from God vnto a citie of Galilie, named <hi>Nazaret,</hi> to a virgin affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anced to a man, whoſe name was <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> of the houſe of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and the virgins name was <hi>Marie.</hi> And the Angel went in vnto her, and ſaid: Haile, thou, that art freelie beloued: the Lord is with thee, bleſſed art thou among women. And when ſhe ſaw him, ſhe was troubled at his ſaying, and thought what maner ſalutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that ſhould be. Then the Angell ſaid vnto her: feare not, <hi>Marie:</hi> for thou haſt found fauour with God: for lo, thou ſhalt <q>conceiue in thy womb, and beare a ſonne, and ſhalt call his name Ieſus. He ſhall be great, and ſhalbe called the ſonne of the Moſt-high. And the Lord God ſhal giue vnto him the throne of his father <hi>Dauid,</hi> and he ſhall reigne ouer the houſe of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> for euer, and of his kingdome ſhalbe no end, Luke. 1, 26 &amp;c. S. <hi>Peter</hi> thus: Men and brethren, I may boldlie ſpeake vnto you of the patriarke <hi>Dauid</hi> &amp;c. ſeeing he was a Prophet, and knew that God had</q>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:28175:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſworne with an oth to him, that of the frute of his loines he would raiſe vp Chriſt, concerning the fleſh, to ſet him v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his throne, he knowing this before, ſpake of the reſurrection of Chriſt, that his ſoul ſhould not be left in graue, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his fleſh ſee corruption &amp;c. Act. 2, 29 &amp;c. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> in this wiſe: of this mans ſeede (ſpeaking of king <hi>Dauid</hi>) hath God, according to his promiſe, raiſed vp to Iſrael, the Sauiour Ieſus &amp;c. Act. 13, 23 &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> had wonderfull reuelations of Chriſt, in ſo much that he by faith (as well as <hi>Abraham.</hi> Ioh. 8, 56) well near a 1000. years before ſaw Chriſt crucified, and foretold what ſpeeches he ſhould ſpeake vpon the croſſe, Pſal. 22, 1. Mat. 27, 46. Pſ. 31, 5. Luke. 23, 46. Alſo of <hi>Iudas</hi> his treaſon, Pſalm. 41, 9. Ioh. 13, 18. and curſed end, Pſ. 109, 8. Act. 1, 16. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe how the ſcoffing ſcribes, prieſtes, phariſees &amp; elders ſhould mocke Chriſt, Pſal. 22, verſ 7. 8. Mat. 27, 43. and the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage ſouldiers deale with him, Pſal. 22. verſ. 16. 18. and 69, 21. Mat. 27, 48. Ioh. 19, 34. Luke. 24, 44. He ſpake alſo of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
            </p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:28175:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Now let vs conſider, that like as this ſeede Chriſt Ieſus, (being the day-ſpring from an high to viſite vs, Luke. 1, 78. and the true light of the world, Ioh. 8, 12. A light to be reueiled to the gentiles (as was<note place="margin">Numb. 24. 17.</note> prefigured by the ſtarre, Mat. 2, 1 &amp;c.) and the glorie of the people of Iſrael, Luke. 2. 32) is called the Sunne of righteouſneſſe to ariſe with health vnder his wings vnto them, that feare the Lord, Malac. 4, 2. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo, after the manner of the riſing of the Sunne, we haue ſeene Chriſtes mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation vnto the world, for the Sunne, being readie to ariſe, firſt ſendeth forth ſome ſmall glimſe of his brightnes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto we may compare the miſterie of that aphoriſme: The ſeede of the woman ſhall breake the ſerpents head, Gen. 3, 15. Then it enlargeth the ſame brightneſſe with more light, to which <hi>Noahs</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie may be likened: Bleſſed be the Lord God of <hi>Sem,</hi> Gen. 9, 26. Afterward aſcending higher, and approching nearer vnto vs, it putteth forth his glimmering beames of clearer light, whereto we may reſemble the plainer promiſes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning Chriſt communicated with thoſe after-ages
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:28175:14"/> of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Geneſ. 12. verſ. 2. 3. of <hi>Iſaak,</hi> Gen. 26. verſ. 3. 4. of <hi>Iacob,</hi> Gen. 28. 14. of <hi>Dauid,</hi> 2 Sam. 7, 12 &amp;c. At length it diſcouereth it ſelfe, and appeareth out o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penlie, whereunto Chriſtes birth and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie anſwereth, Mat. 2, 1 &amp;c. and laſtlie, it mounteth vp aboue the earth, moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouflie in lightning, quickning and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting the earth, &amp; all things thereupon: And to this accordeth Chriſtes exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and lifting vp from the earth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by himſelfe was glorified, Ioh. 12, 23. drew all men vnto him, verſ. 32. &amp; gaue them power beleeuing in his name, to be the ſonnes of God, Ioh. 1, 12. And in this wiſe the holie Scripture ſeemeth to manifeſt vnto men, from the beginning of the world, the eternall purpoſe and decree of God touching Chriſt our redeemer. As may alſo appeare by thoſe metaphoricall ſpeeches drawen from the ſunnes ariſing often vſed in the Scriptures, as: Deut. 33, 2. Micah. 5, 2. Mal. 4, 2. wherefore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle calleth <hi>Moſes</hi> law a vail, or couering, 2. Cor. 3, 14 And Saint <hi>Peter</hi> likeneth the ſame law and old teſtament (i. the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures written before the comming of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:28175:15"/> Chriſt) vnto a light that ſhineth in a dark place, 2 Pet. 1, 19. But contrariwiſe in the ſame verſe, he nameth Chriſt, or the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of Chriſt crucified (that is the new teſtament, the day-dawne, and day-ſtar, which (as <hi>Zacharie Iohn Baptiſts</hi> father prophecied) ſhould giue light to them, that ſit in darkeneſſe, and in the ſhadow of death, and guide our feet into the way of peace, Luke. 1, 79. And concerning Chriſtes diſſoluing and loſing the works of the Deuill in man, that thing he effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted through his paſſion, as he was man, 2. Cor. 13, 4. 1 Pet. 3, 18 &amp; 4, 1. &amp; by his reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as he was God, Ioh. 10, 18. 1 Cor. 6, 14. and 15, 15. The Apoſtle in a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full breuitie wrappeth vp both theſe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects ſaying: Ieſus Chriſt was deliuered to death for our ſinnes, and <note n="s" place="margin">As the Action of Iſaaks offring (being a figure of Chriſtes) was 3. daies in finiſhing (for the third day he was, after a ſort raiſed from the dead, Gen. 22, 4. Heb. 11. 19.) ſo the ſpace of Chriſtes offring himſelf was three daies, from his death to his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. Mat. 16. 21. 1 Cor. 15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4</note> roſe againe for our iuſtification, Rom. 4, 25. As alſo yet more wonderfullie he abridgeth the whole ſumme of chriſtian Religion thus: God is manifeſted in the fleſh, iuſtified in the ſpirite, ſeene of Angels, preached vnto the Gentiles, beleeued on in the world, and receiued vp in glorie, 1 Tim. 3. 16. Hauing ſpoiled the principalities and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:28175:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> powers, and made ſhew of them openly,<note place="margin">Read Mat. 12, 40. &amp; Hoſ. 6, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; 13, 14.</note> and triumphed ouer them in his croſſe, Col. 2, 15. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſtroying through death, him, that had the power of death, that is, the deuill, that he might deliuer all them which for feare of death, were all their life time ſubiect to bondage, Heb. 2. verſ. 14. 15. we reade in holy ſcripture of three ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall and famous <note n="t" place="margin">Three notable deliuerances of Gods church, and all at one time of the yeare.</note> deliuerances, or rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, with their iuſt times and moneths of the yeare by moſt certaine cumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces deſcribed. 1 <hi>Abrahams</hi> calling out of Chaldea from idolatrie into the land of<note place="margin">an. mundi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>709.</note> promiſe, Gen. 11, 31. &amp; 12, 1. and 15, 13. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. 12. verſ. 26, 40. 2 Iſraels redemption out of Egypt, Exod. 12, 41. Gal. 3. verſ. 16. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2509"/> 17. 3 The deliuerance of the Iewes from <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3456"/> Babylon by <hi>Cyrus</hi> king of Perſia, Ezra. 1, 1 &amp;c. 2 Chron. 36, 10. Dan. 9. verſ. 2. 21 &amp;c. All which were done at the ſpring of the yeare, to ſhadow and repreſent vnto vs this fourth and generall redemption of man-kinde from Satan, ſinne, hell, death &amp;c. wrought by Chriſt, what time the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chall lambe (a type of Chriſt the verie lamb of God, that taketh away the ſinnes of the world) was to be killed and eaten,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:28175:16"/> Exo. 12. verſ. 6. 8. Mat. 26, 18. For from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> going out of the commaundement of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rus</hi> touching the Iewes returne home a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaine vnto the death of Chriſt, the Ang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Gabriel</hi> (whoſe miniſterie the Lord vſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the meſſage of Chriſtes humanitie, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> here to <hi>Daniel,</hi> to <hi>Zacharias,</hi> Luke. 1, 19<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> verſ. 26. 27. And (no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doubt) to <hi>Ioſeph</hi> thriſe, Mat. 1, 20. and 2. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 13. 19) certifieth <hi>Daniel,</hi> that there ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be 70 weekes, which (after the propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call weeke, a day for a yeare, as Ezech. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 6) conteine 490 yeares. Dan. 9, 24 &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but Chriſt was to be killed in the mids o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the laſt weeke, Dan. 9, 27. then were ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3943"/> iuſt 487 yeares. And according to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> time of the Angels apparence to <hi>Daniel</hi> verſ. 21) about the euening ſacrifice, which in praier, and oblation, was fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ninth hower to the twelfth: as likewiſe at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ninth hower Chriſt gaue vp the ghoſt Mat. 27. verſ. 46. 50.</p>
            <p>The Iewes diuiding the day (from ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe to ſun-ſet) into 12 howers, Ioh. 11, 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> began their euening praier at the ninth hower (that is, as we accompt, at three o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the clocke after-noone) Act. 3, 1. which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:28175:16"/> three howers, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> till the euening <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acrifice of the lambe was offered at twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght, Exod. 29, 41. what time alſo Chriſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>odie (the true ſacrifice of our ſinnes, Iſai. 3, 10. Epheſ. 5, 2. 1 Pet. 2, 24.) was taken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om the croſſe, Mat. 27. verſ. 57, 58.</p>
            <p>No maruell now (the time of Chriſtes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omming ſo long and ſo plainlie told be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore, and recorded in <hi>Daniels</hi> prophecie) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> S. <hi>Iohn</hi> note this in the Iewes eſpeciallie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a monſtrous (and yet general) vnkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe, proceeding of their wilfull igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance of Gods mercifull viſiting them by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is owne <note n="v" place="margin">Manie of the Iewes of that time waited co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallie for Chriſts comming, as Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph of Arimathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a, Luke, 23, 51. fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Simeon, An Phanuel, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe other, Luk. 2 verſ. 25. 36. And in the yeare that Chriſt ſuffred, Caiaphas proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied that one ſhould die for the people &amp;c. Ioh. 11 49. not ſpeaking that from Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els writings, but God putting the truth in his mouth (as he did in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lams aſſe, Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, 22, 28) he vttered thereby his owne malice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which he bare in his minde to kill Chriſt: ſo the caitife blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied with one voice.</note> ſonne: that Chriſt Ieſus came <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto his owne, and his owne receiued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im not, Ioh. 1, 11. our Lord therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>harplie rebuketh thoſe Phariſies, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>adduces, for their groſſe ignorance of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſignes and times of his comming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ong them: telling them that they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etter ſeene in the face of the ſkie, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore wether-wiſe to diſcerne faire daies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd tempeſts, then skilfull to know the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mes of the Lords viſitation, Mat. 16<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his their generall ignorance, euen at his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt farewell to the citie, moued him to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eepe ouer Ieruſalem, and through ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:28175:17"/> ſobbes, euen to wan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> words to expreſſe his griefe for their wofull miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſaying: O if thou hadſt knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the leaſt in this thy day thoſe things, which belong to thy peace! but now are they hid from thine eies, Luke 19, 42. They had diuerſe ſignes to haue put them in minde of his comming, as the departure of the <note n="w" place="margin">Read Dan. 2, 44. After the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie of Babylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there were no kings in Iewrie, for the ſtate was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned by depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the tribe of Iudah: but that Herod, Mat. 2, 1 &amp;c. being an Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bian by nation, &amp; deſcended of the ſtocke of the kings of that fourth kingdome, Dan. 2, 40 reigned king in Iudea (&amp; ſo the ſcepter was tranſlated from the tribe of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah) when Chriſt was borne.</note> ſcepter from the tribe of Iudah, Gen. 49, 10. And the ſending of <hi>Elias</hi> the Prophet, Malac 4, 5. not that verie <hi>Elias</hi> himſelfe ſhould riſe againe to reproue, as <hi>Sirachides</hi> ſuppoſed, Eccleſ. 48, 4 &amp;c. And as the common opinion of the Iewes and <note n="t" place="margin">Iohn Baptiſt denieth that he is Elias, Ioh. 1, 21. but his deniall is after this ſenſe of the Scribes, for ſo his queſtioners ment it. See He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rods feare that 10. Baptiſt ſhould be riſen againe, Mat. 14, 2. The Iowes had long before this ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e admitted Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras his Mete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſychôſis, as alſo h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s profane opinion of the good &amp; ill angel attending each one, 2 Machab. 11, 6. Acts. 12, 15.</note> Scribes was, Mat. 17, 10: but that <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> ſhould go before Chriſt in the ſpirit and power of <hi>Elias,</hi> as <hi>Gabriel</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preteth <hi>Malachis</hi> meaning to <hi>Zacharias,</hi> Luke. 1, 17. &amp; Chriſt maketh it plaine, Mat. 11, 14. This finall blindneſſe in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell <hi>Moſes</hi> by the ſpirit foreſaw, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore braſt out with this hearty wiſh of their only happineſſe: Oh that they were wiſe, then they would vnderſtand this: they would co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider their latter end! Deut. 32, 29. with ſorrow inough the Prophet doubled this complaint: who is blind,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:28175:17"/> but my ſeruant? or deafe, as my meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, that I ſent? who is blinde as the <note n="x" place="margin">He alludeth to the name Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth viſible peace: for the Lord had ſet it in the middes of the nations, as a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle in their ſight of all peace and proſperitie to his people: but the Iewes brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereof, were yet vainly confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of peace, which thus the prophet repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, Ezech. 5, 5. Ier. 7, 4. and our Lord, Luke. 19, 42.</note> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed-with-peace? Iſai. 42, 19. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Sauiour, as he went to the croſſe, turning backe to thoſe wailing women, which lamenting him, little thought of their owne calamities, that ſhould ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie enſue, mercifullie forewarneth them: Weepe not for me, ye daughters of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, but weepe for your ſelues, and for your children: for behold the daies will come, when men ſhall ſay: Bleſſed are the baren, and the wombes, that neuer bare, &amp; the breſtes, that neuer gaue ſucke, Luk. 23. verſ. 28. 29. But I am here caried farther then I purpoſed, yet not ſo far from my purpoſe, whereunto I returne. S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith that this Ieſus Chriſt, the iuſt, is our aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat with the father, &amp; the reconciliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for all our ſinnes, 1 Iohn. 2, verſe. 1. 2. And that his bloud clenſeth vs from al ſinne, 1 Iohn. 1, 7. for (as the Baptiſt ſaith) he is the lamb of God, which taketh away the ſinne of the world, Ioh. 1, 29. <q>Neither is their (as S. <hi>Pet.</hi> witneſſeth) ſaluation in any other: for amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is geuen none other name vnder heauen whereby we muſt be ſaued,</q>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:28175:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> Acts. 4, 12. To him alſo giue all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets witneſſe, that through his name, all that beleeue in him ſhall receiue remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinnes, Act. 10, 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Therefore the true Chriſtian touching all the worke of his ſaluation, both in heart beleeueth, &amp; with mouth confeſſeth with the Pſalmiſt thus: Whom haue I in heauen but thee? And I haue deſired none in the earth with thee Pſa. 73, 25. He alone is God all-ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, Gen 17, 1. mightie and ſufficient to ſaue, Iſai. 63, 1. neither is there anie other that heareth our words, Iſai, 41, 26. and 63. verſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 16. Wherefore <hi>Dauid</hi> calleth him: O thou that heareſt the praier, Pſal. 65. 2. And Iſay, ſetteth downe the verie fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me of euerie Chriſtians faith and confeſſion thus: Onely in the Lord touching me (ſhall he ſay) is <note n="y" place="margin">Righteouſnes, in the orginall t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngue is red in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mber, to ſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ifie vnto vs th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> all our righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſe is of the Lord, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat we ſhould neuer once open our mouth to iuſtifie our ſelues, Eze. 10, 63.</note> all my righteouſneſſe &amp; ſtrength, Iſai. 45, 24. for Chriſt Ieſus (who is al in al, Col. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 11. Ioh. 1, 9. Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 9, 16. Eph. 1, 23 Phil. 2, 13) of God is made vnto vs wiſedome, &amp; righteouſneſſe, &amp; ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, &amp; redemption, that God alone might haue al the glorie, 1 Cor. 1. verſ. 30. 31. Now the meanes to obtaine this righteouſneſſe in Chriſt, is by hearing the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:28175:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> word of God (either red: Exod. 24, 7. Deu. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>1, 11. Ioh. 20, 31. Act. 15, 21. Eph. 3, 4. Col. 4, 16, 1 Theſ 5, 27. or Preached: Act. 8, 35 &amp;c and 16. verſ. 14. 32. 1 Cor. 14. verſ. 24 25) aſſuredly to beleeue all the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God in his ſon our Sauiour, 2 Cor. 1 20. 1 Ioh. 5. verſ. 10. 11) applying them to thy ſelfe thus, That Chriſt Ieſus died for my ſinnes, and roſe againe for my iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, Rom 4, 25. And the Apoſtle ſaith, <q>if thou ſhalt confeſſe with thy mouth the Lord Ieſus, and beleeue in thy hart that God raiſed him vp from the dead,</q> thou ſhalt be ſaued: for with the heart man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth vnto righteouſneſſe, and with the mouth man confeſſeth to ſaluation, for the ſcripture ſaith: whoſoeuer belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in him ſtall not be aſhamed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om. 10, 9 &amp;c. The Iarler at Philippi asking <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> what he ſhould do to be ſaued, they anſwered: Beleeue in the Lord Ieſus, and thou ſhalt be ſaued, Act 16. 20 &amp;c. The Scribe demaunding of Chriſt what he ſhould do to inherit eternall life, is ſent to the law, and word of God to marke what he readeth there, Luke. 10, 25.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:28175:19"/>
            <p>But here (by the occaſion of our Lords queſtion, how readeſt thou?) pawſe we a little, and aduiſedlie let vs conſider the force and efficacie of reading the word of God. The reading of Gods word, and preaching of the ſame, are the two onely, and ordinarie meanes, whereby (through the working of the ſpirit) the Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueieth his word into our heartes: both which are expreſſed by one word in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew <hi>Karà,</hi> which ſignifieth to crie, or call: to proclaime, pronounce, or preach: to declare, or reade, Exod. 24, 7. Deut. 31, 11 &amp;c. After which the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be feigned, bearing the ſame ſenſe of proclaiming, preaching or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing, Iſai. 58, 1. Reuelat. 5, 2. As like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe S. <hi>Iames</hi> taketh preaching and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the word of God both for one, Act. 15, 21. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 1. 25. &amp; touching that place: How ſhall they hear without a preacher? Rom. 10 14. It is principallie ment of the firſt publiſhing the glad tidings of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, aſwell by Chriſt him ſelfe, Iſai. 9, 2. &amp; 41, 27. and 49, 6. and 52, 7 &amp;c. Mat. 9, 35. &amp; 17, 5. Rom. 15, 8. Hebr. 1, 2. and 2, 3. as by his Apoſtles, firſt to the Iewes, Mat. 10. verſ.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:28175:19"/> 5. 6: after to the Gentiles in all the world, Mat. 28, 19. Rom. 16, 26. Coloſ. 1, 23. Confer Iſai. 52. verſ. 7. 8. 9. 10. with Rom. 10. verſe. 12. 14. 15: for both the Prophet, and the Apoſtle ſpeake of vniting Chriſtes whole church of Iewes &amp; Gentiles, which could not be called, &amp; conioined but by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Goſpel, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, Epheſ. 2, 11 &amp;c. and it is blaſphemie to derogat from that excellent and effectual ordinance of God, the reading of his word, that it ſhould not aſwel beget faith in the hearers, if with an honeſt and good heart they reade (or heare it red) &amp; keepe the ſame, Luk. 8, 15, as confirme and increaſe faith in them, being begotten by the ſame word, 1 Ioh. 1, 4: for the word of God in it ſelfe is equally heard, whether it be red, Luke. 24, 45, or preached, Act. 16, 14. &amp; equally edifieth, if it be vnderſtood, Act. 8, 30, and withal tempered with faith in them that heare it, Hebr. 4, 2. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle earneſtlie chargeth the reading his epiſtles, Col. 4, 16. 1 Theſ. 5, 27. 2 Theſ. 2, 15. And to that end alſo was the Goſpell written, as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> affirmeth, Ioh. 20, 31. read Epheſ. 3. verſ. 3, 4: This I
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:28175:20"/> write not to mainteine vnlearned readers in the church, much leſſe to make them equall to the preachers of the word, for I deſire with Saint <hi>Paul<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> that they all could preach, 1 Cor. 14, 5. as their place requireth of them, Ioh. 21, 15. Acts. 20, 28. 1 Cor 12, 28. 1 Tim. 3, 2. 2 Tim. 2, 2. and 4, 2. 1 Pet. 5, 2. yea rather I wiſh with <hi>Moſes,</hi> that all the Lords people were Prophets, Numb. 11, 29 (for I well know, and willinglie confeſſe that the preaching of the word ought to be preferred before the reading of the ſame, becauſe of our dulneſſe, Iſai. 28. verſ. 9, 10. Hebr. 5, 11:) but my writing is onely to this end, that we ſhould not neglect (as we do) ſo excellent a benefit, and bleſſed ordinance of God, as is the reading of his word, being ſo ſeuerely commaunded, and highlie recommended to his church. Now let vs go forward: The holie Scriptures are <note n="z" place="margin">The authority and power of the holie Scriptures.</note> able (&amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſufficient) to make vs wiſe vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, through the faith which is in Chriſt Ieſus: <q>for the whole ſcripture is giuen by inſpiration of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and is profitable to teach and improue, to correct and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct in righteouſneſſe,</q> that the man of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:28175:20"/> God may be abſolute, being made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ect vnto all good workes, 2 Tim. 3, 15 &amp;c. when our Lord would controll anie er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our, he vſuallie obiected, Haue yee not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed? Mat. 12. verſ. 3. 5. and 19, 4. and 21, 42. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd 22, 31 &amp;c. ſignifying thereby that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acred Scriptures ought to be our onely direction and guide, &amp; therefore the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie Ghoſt calleth the word of God a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erne vnto our feet, and a light vnto our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aths, Pſal. 119, 105. Prou. 6, 23. wherefore <hi>Moſes</hi> exhorting the Iſraelits to embrace and obſerue the law &amp; word of God, tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth them that it is not onely their wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and vnderſtanding in the ſight of all people, but euen their life alſo, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>engthning of their daies in the land: and that all the people of the earth ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of them therefore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Deut. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6 and 28, 10. and 32, 47. wherefore the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth of the neglect thereof, ſaying: I haue written vnto them the great things of my law, but they were counted as a ſtrange thing, Hoſ. 8, 12.</p>
            <p>But the holie Ghoſt, by the pen of S. <hi>Paul</hi> hath ſet downe an inuincible <note n="*" place="margin">S. Pauls gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reaſon for the iuſt triall of true religion.</note> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to hold vs to the word of God, in all
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:28175:21"/> pocriſie. And he deſcrieth them by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> two moſt certaine tokens in ſtead of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that they ſhould commaund to <note n="a" place="margin">And yet both theſe are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the word of God, Gen. 1, 28. and 9. verſ. 1. 3. Deut. 12, 20. Therefore this is a ſpeciall note of antichriſt ſo to oppoſe himſelfe againſt God, 1 Tim. 4, 3. And touching our meats, by grace, or thanke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>giuing, they are ſactified, 1 Tim. 4, 4. which thing (beſides that our Lord himſelfe vſuallie obſerued, Mat. 14, 19 &amp;c) was alſo commaunded in the law. Deut 8, 10, and practized, 1 Sam. 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 13.</note> abſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from diuerſe meats, and forbid mariage mong their votaries, 1 Tim. 4, 1 &amp;c. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that they ſhould be louers of their ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelues, couetous, boaſters, proude, cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpeakers, diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to parents, vnthan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, vnholie, without naturall affectio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> truce-breakers, falſe-accuſers, intemper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fierce, deſpicers of them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which are goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> traitors, headie, high-minded, louers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pleaſures more the louers of God, hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a ſhew of godlineſſe, but haue deni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the power thereof: (and he aduiſeth Turne away therefore from ſuch, 2 Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 3, 2 &amp;c. S. <hi>Peter</hi> writeth likewiſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they ſhould teach damnable hereſies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen denying the Lord, that boug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them, which they do in ſeeking right<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſneſſe by their owne workes, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Saints merits: by ſuborning ſtrange i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> terceſſours with Chriſt, or beſides Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by their Maſſe, purgatorie, &amp;c. by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which they denie the force and effica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Chriſtes death, and the merits of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> paſſion, making him to die in vaine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:28175:21"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny benefit to them, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> telleth hoſe ceremonitarie Galatians<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Gal. 2, 21. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd 5, 2. and that through couetouſneſſe<note place="margin">Papiſticall mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and their warehouſe.</note> with fained wordes, they ſhould make marchandiſe of vs, 2 Pet. 2, 1 &amp;c. Saint <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ohn</hi> ſetteth open the pedlarie-packe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir marchandiſe, by which their wares we may well perceiue what marchants Saint <hi>Peter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> meaneth, among which marchandiſe Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> reckoneth the ſoules of men, Reuelat. 18, 11 &amp;c Read the place, for it is notable, and you ſhall ſee that the verie wares wil plainly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray the marchants vnto you. We haue ſeene before that it is ſinne to make either angel, the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> or any other ſaint our aduocate, mediator, or interceſſor to God for vs, not onely becauſe the holie ſcriptures appoint none ſuch: but for that alſo that it is Chriſts office alone, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe witneſſeth, No ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but by me, Ioh. 14, 6. for there is one God, &amp; one Mediator betweene God &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. which is the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt Ieſus, 1 Tim. 2, 5. And touching Chriſtes mediation ſee a manifeſt exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, Zechar. 1, 12 &amp;c. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the prophet <hi>Iſai</hi> calleth him the angel
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:28175:22"/> of Gods face, or preſence, Iſai. 63, 9. Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 8, 34. Hebr. 7, 25. for by Ieſus Chriſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> true chriſtians offer the ſacrifice of prai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alwaies to God (that is) the frute of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lippes, which confeſſe his name, Hebr. 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 15. Reuel. 8. verſ. 3. 4. Let vs therefore (fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowing the counſell of the Apoſtle) g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> boldlie vnto Chriſtes throne of grace (fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he is our High-ſacrificer, and Mediator<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hebr. 3, 1. and 5, 5 &amp;c. and 6, 20) that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may receiue mercie, &amp; find grace to help<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in time of neede, Heb. 4, 16. The Pſalmiſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the more to incourage vs to frequent this throne of grace, exemplifieth vnto vs, by a compariſon of the leſſer, how readili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we ſhall ſpeede in our ſuites at Chriſtes throne, ſaying: <hi>Moſes, Aaron</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> called vpon the Lord for pardon, &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he heard them graciouſlie, Pſa. 99, 6. How much more then may we be ſure to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine either for our ſelues, or for others, by the interceſſion of Chriſt the ſonne of God? Rom. 8, 34.</p>
            <p>And here a little to enlarge this matter for our further inſtruction, let vs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that Chriſt is our Prophet, our High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſt, and our King, which three offices
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:28175:22"/> of Chriſt the Apoſtle plainlie deſcribeth, Hebr. 1. namely his propheticall office, verſ. 2. his prieſt-hod in theſe words: who hath by himſelfe purged our ſinnes. And his kinglie dignitie thus: And ſitteth at the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the maieſty in the higheſt places &amp;c. v. 3. &amp; 10, 12. Chriſt is therfore <hi>A great Prophet</hi> to interpret the mind &amp; wil of God his father vnto vs, Deu. 18. v. 18. 19. Ioh. 1, 18. &amp; 6, 45. Act. 3, 22 &amp;c. Ephe. 2, 17. Heb. 1, 2. touching our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption, &amp; eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chriſt, purpoſed with God before the world was made, Epheſ. 1, 4. by whoſe ſpirit the Prophets in olde time ſpake Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 6, 6. 1 Pet. 1, 11. &amp; 3, 19. 2 Pet. 1, 21. <hi>An euerlaſting King</hi> to rule vs, Iſai. 9. v. 6. 7. Ezech. 37. verſ. 22. 24. Dan. 2, 24 &amp;c. Hoſ. 3, 5. Pſal. 132, 11 &amp;c. Luk. 1, 32 &amp;c. <hi>And an High-Prieſt</hi> to reconcile vs vnto God his father, Iſai. 42, 6. Malac. 3, 1. Col. 1, 20 &amp;c. 1 Tim. 2, 5. Hebr. 7, 24 &amp;c. and 9. verſ. 11. 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by offring vp his owne bodie in ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice vpon the alter of the croſſe to paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Gods wrath for our ſinnes, Hebr. 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 10. 1 Pet. 2, 24. which vnſpotted, and holie ſacrifice of his immaculate bodie was ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in it ſelfe to ſatiſfie for all the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:28175:23"/> in the world, 2 Cor. 5, 14. 1 Tim. 2, 6. Hebr. 2, 9: but effectuall onely for the ſinnes of the elect, and beleeuers, Iohn. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 12. which the holie Scripture calleth, The manie, Iſai 53. verſe. 11. 12. Dan. 9, 27. Mat. 26, 28. Hebr. 9, 28. This his prieſthood the high prieſts of the law prefigured, Exod. 28. Hebr. 5 and 7. And Chriſt hath made all chriſtians, prieſts vnto God, Reuel. 1, 6, to offer vnto him their bodies, Rom. 12, 1 a contrite heart, Pſalm. 51, 17. praiſe and thankeſgiuing, Pſal. 116, 17. Hebr. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 15. and liberalitie towards the poor, Phil. 4, 18. Hebr. 13, 16. Iob. 29, 13. Pſa, 16<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3. Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching his priuate life, from his birth till his baptiſme, the Euangeliſts write little, becauſe his humane actions in that ſpace little concerned vs, ſauing that his whole life was poore and miſerable, Iſai 53, 3, that we through his pouertie might be made rich, 2 Cor. 8, 9. he increaſed dailie in wiſedome, ſtature, and fauour with God and men, and was ſubiect to his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and exerciſed <hi>Ioſephs</hi> carpentarie art. Luke. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. verſ. 51. 52. wherefore ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the Iewes call him, The Carpenter <hi>Maries</hi> ſonne, Mark. 6, 3. which name
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:28175:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> though they gaue him in deriſion, yet was it more honourable then they imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: for he was indeed, The great Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter of the world, Col. 1, 16. Hebr. 3, 4. The Iewes knew well that he was vtterly vnlearned, and ſo they confeſſe, Ioh. 7, 15. as alſo his Diſciples were, Acts. 4, 13. whereof Saint <hi>Paul</hi> yeeldeth vs this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, That our faith ſhould not be in the wiſedome of men, but in the power of God, 1 Cor. 2, 5. Therefore ſaith Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> If any man ſpeake, let him talke as the wordes of God, 1 Pet. 4, 11. And Chriſt denieth that his doctrine was his owne (as he was man) but of God, Iohn. 7, 16: for indeed he was taught of God, Iſai. 50. verſ. 4. 5. And therefore was able, when he was but twelue yeares old, to aſke the learned doctors ſuch queſtions, that all that heard him, were aſtonied at his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and anſweres, Luke. 2. verſ. 46. 47. Of his queſtions ſee an example, Mat. 22, 41 &amp;c. At the age of 30<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yeares he was baptized, Luk. 3, 23. as at that age alſo the Leuiticall prieſts were fully admitted to execute their office, Num. 4, 47. Chriſt (as it ſhould ſeeme) was baptized the 15.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:28175:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> day of September, in the feaſt of taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles, Leuit. 23, 34: for ſo are there iuſt thoſe 1260. daies, Reuelat. 12, 6, from his baptiſme to the 14. day of March (3. years &amp; an halfe after) when he ſuffred his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, according to the law, Exod. 12, 6. Mat. 26, 20 &amp;c. which time of 3. yeares and an half (being the ſpace of the cruel perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the Iewes church vnder <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> Dan. 12, 11. 1 Machab. 1, 57. and 4, 52. 6, 16. and 2 Machab. 11, 33. who as he was the firſt tyrant, that euer durſt attempt to alter thé law of God, &amp; religion of the Iewes, Dan. 8, 11. &amp; 11, 38. 2 Mac. 6, 1 &amp;c. ſo for his monſtrous and beaſtlie rage againſt the High-ſaints, the people of God, Dan. 7, 8. he might moſt fitly ſerue Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> to patterne antichriſt (an other <hi>Antiochus</hi>) aſwell for the like barbarous crueltie againſt the lightes of the world, Phil. 2, 15. the ſtarres, Dan. 12, 3, Hebr. 11, 12. and Hoſt of heauen, the true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Dan. 8, 10 &amp;c. Reuelat. 8, 12. and 12, 4. and for the equall power giuen him of God thereunto, Dan. 7, 21. and 8, 12. and 11, 36. Reuel. 13, 7. as alſo for the ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blable meanes of ſtrength to accompliſh
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:28175:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> his tyrannie, Dan. 7, 7. Reuel. 13, 1. and 17. ver. 37 &amp;c. And laſtly for the ſame iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and damnation of them both, by booke euidence, recording all their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs againſt Gods people, to be torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the fierie lake for euer, Dan. 7 verſ. 10. 11. Reuel. 19, 20. and 20, 12. was likewiſe the ſpace that Chriſt the head of his church, Eph. 1, 22. indured all indignities, euen to the ſhamefull death of the croſſe, Phil. 2, 8, Hebr. 12, 2. Iſai. 50, 6. as the Prince of our ſaluation conſecrated through afflictions, becauſe he that ſanctifieth, &amp; they, which are ſanctified, are all of one, Hebr. 2. veſ. 10. 11. And this ſpace is alſo expreſſed ſometime by halfe a propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call weeke, anſwerable to <hi>Daniels</hi> mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weeke, Dan. 9, 27. viz. three daies and an halfe, Reuelat. 11, 9. ſometime by 42 mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, Reuel. 13, 5. ſometime by a time, two times and halfe a time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Dan. 7, 25. and 12, 7. Reuel. 12, 14. All which varieties ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe yet one ſpace of time, to ſignifie ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a certaine meaſure of afflictions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined in Gods euerlaſting purpoſe to conforme his Church (both of the Iewes and Gentiles) to the image of his owne
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:28175:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſonne, Rom. 8, 29. 2 Cor. 4, 11. 1 Pet. 5, 10. then any certaine time of perſecution, which the church of Chriſt muſt indure according to the will of God, Rom. 6, 6. 2 Cor. 1, 5. and 4, 10. Heb. 10, 36. 1 Pet. 3, 17. And immediatly after his baptiſme he was viſiblie repleniſhed with the holie ſpirit, Mat. 3, 16. Luk. 4, 1. And preſently led by the ſame ſpirit into the wilderneſſe to be tempted of the deuil, Mat. 4, 1. Heb. 2, 18. and 4, 15. where he being among wild beaſtes, Mark. 1, 13. which of old time were wont to frequent the deſerts along the riuer Iorden, Zechar. 11, 3. continued faſting 40. daies in holie meditation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he entred that great worke of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers buſineſſe, which was inioined him of God, in accompliſhing the truth of <hi>Moſes</hi> law, by ſealing vp, and fulfilling, the viſion and Prophet, and aboliſhing the dailie ſacrifice &amp; oblation of the law, Dan. 9. ve. 24. 27. through the one oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of himſelf, Heb. 9, 14. &amp; 10, 14. wherby he cancelled the handwriting of the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall law, which continuallie reuiued &amp; teſtified our ſinnes againſt vs, Col. 2, 14. and thereby brought in euerlaſting righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:28175:25"/> for vs all, Dan. 9, 24. Hebr. 10, 14. <hi>Moſes</hi> likewiſe at the giuing of the law had continued 40. daies faſting in the Lords preſence vppon the mount, Exod. 34, 28. And <hi>Elias</hi> alſo at the reſtoring of the ſame law, was 40. daies miraculouſlie ſuſtained without any food, 1 King. 19. v. 8. 14. which miraculous abſtine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Elias,</hi> and of Chriſt, ſheweth the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie perfection of the law in it ſelfe, Rom. 7, 12. which was deliuered, reſtored, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed by one and the ſame miracle, though, through the infirmitie of our fleſhe, Rom. 8, 3, it could not yet with all that perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make vs perfect, Heb. 7, 19. and 10, 1. but Chriſts one offring of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath made perfect for euer them, that are ſanctified, Heb. 10, 14. Thus therefore in the end of thoſe 40. daies, hauing put the Tempter to flight, he came forth and preached the glad tydings of our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Mat. 4, 17. and 9, 35. euen the generall Iubilie of our euerlaſting freedome from the captiuitie of Sathan, ſinne, hell, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall death, Leuit, 25. verſ. 9. 10. Luk 4. verſ. 17. 18 &amp;c. And theſe three orders namely, kings, high-prieſts, and Prophets
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:28175:26"/> were ordeined according to the law by annointing, Exod. 40, 13. 1. Sam, 16, 13. 1. King 19, 16. to ſhadow vnto vs the plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full graces of Gods ſpirit, which was in them by meaſure, Act. 1, 5. Eph. 4, 7. 1 Ioh. 2. verſ. 20. 27. and 4, 13: but in Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meaſure, Pſalm. 45, 7. Luk. 4, 18. Ioh. 1, 16. and 3, 34. and 10, 36. Acts. 10, 38. as in whom are hid all the treaſures of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge, Col. 2, 3. becauſe in him dwelleth all the fulneſſe of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head reallie, Col. 2, 9: for it pleaſed the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that in him ſhould all fulneſſe dwel, Col. 1, 19, and of his fulneſſe haue all we receiued, and grace vpon grace, Ioh. 1, 16. Eph. 4, 7. Tit. 3, 6. Pſal. 68, 19. God hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden all ſimilitudes and likeneſſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny<note place="margin">Images.</note> thing either in heauen, in earth, or in the ſea (which lying in his chanell, as it were vnderbeareth the earth, Pſal. 24 2) to worſhip them, or him thereby, vppon paine of eternall death, not onely on the ſpirituall adulterers themſelues (that is, the breakers of that ſpirituall wedlocke, Ier. 31, 32. Ezech. 16, 8) but euen to the 3. and 4. generation of their adulterous po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie, Exod. 20, 5. Read Hoſ. 2. verſ. 2. 3.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:28175:26"/> 4. 5. And <hi>Moſes</hi> exhorting the Iſraelites (as knowing that he ſhould verie ſhortly after be taken from them) chargeth them diligently to attend to the law and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of the Lord, and eſpeciallie that they ſhould beware of idolatrie: for the Lord (ſaith he) ſpake vnto you out of the mids of the fire, and yee heard the voice of the words, but ſaw no ſimilitude ſaue a voice. Take therefore good heed vnto your ſelues (for you ſaw no image in the day that the Lord ſpake vnto you in Horeb out of the mids of the fire) that yee corrupt not your ſelues, and make you a grauen image, or repreſentation of any figure, &amp;c. Deut 4. verſ. 12. 15. 16. wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>Moſes</hi> plainlie ſheweth that the Lord of purpoſe with-held from them all ſhew of figure and likeneſſe, cauſing them on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to heare a voice (for none can expreſſe the image of a voice, as ſaith <hi>Eſdras, 4 Eſd.</hi> 5, 37) becauſe they ſhould make no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner image at all: no, though it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for them to imitate the verie image of God himſelfe to worſhip him therby, yet were it vnlawfull for them ſo to doo: for God is a ſpirit, and they that worſhip
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:28175:27"/> him, muſt worſhip him in ſpirit &amp; truth, for the father requireth euen ſuch to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him, Iohn 4, 23 &amp;c. Good works al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo theſe marchants moſt groſlie abuſe making them blaſphemous, and deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie to the due merits of Chriſtes death and paſſion, in in ſeeking <note n="v" place="margin">Albeit true chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians worke not for reward, Rom. 4. 4. but of dutie, Luke. 17, 10 yet our God which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>eth vs to worke, Mat. 20, 1 &amp;c. of his owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ere bountie and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>our, Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 14 15. hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> our workes, Mat. 10. 42. Luke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>3. Rom. 2, 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 6, 10. not for their worthineſſe Iob. 15. verſ. 15. 16. and 14. 4. and 9, 3. Pſal. 130, 3. Luke. 17, 10: but for his own free promiſe, Hebr. 10, 23, and grace, Phil. 2, 13. Tit 3, 5. which he approueth in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Iſai. 43, 25. Micha. 7. verſ. 19. 20. 2 Cor. 12, 9.</note> merit by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for the true Chriſtians ſoule is purified in obeying the truth through the ſpirite, to loue brotherlie without faining, 1 Pet. 1, 22. mortifying the deedes of the bodie by the ſame ſpirit, Roman. 8, 13. for like as by faith he is made the child of God, Gala. 3, 26. euen ſo Chriſt dwelleth in his heart by faith to inable him to comprehend with all Saints the loue of Chriſt, which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth knowledge, that he may be filled with all fulneſſe of God, Epheſ. 3, 17 &amp;c. being made partaker of the godlie nature, in that he fleeth the corruption which is in the world through luſt: ioining vertue with his faith, &amp; with vertue, knowledge: and with knowledge temperance &amp;c. 2 Pet. 1, 4 &amp;c. for a chriſtian is able to do all things through the help of Chriſt, which ſtrengthneth him, Phil. 4, 13. eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to loue his enemies, to bleſſe them, that curſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:28175:27"/> him, to do good to them that hate him, to pray for them which hurt him, and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>indlie reſembling the naturall ſonne of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is heauenlie father, Mat. 5, 44 &amp;c. whoſe workmanſhip he is created in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us vnto good workes, which God hath ordeined, that he ſhould walke in them, Eph. 2, 10. And not to be wearie of well doing, Gal. 6, 9. but (by the grace of God, Heb. 12, 28) to go forward in the worke of his ſaluation, with careful feare &amp; <note n="c" place="margin">There be two kinds of feare in holie ſcripture, a filiall, or childly feare, proceeding of the reuerence of Gods maieſtie, Ier. 5, 22. and loue of his mercie. Pſ. 130, 4. Prou. 28, 14. Iſai. 66, 5. Ier. 2, 19. Mal. 1, 6 1 Ioh. 4, 18. And a ſeruile, or ſlauiſh feare, proceeding from an euill conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce abhorring and trembling at gods preſence, Gen. 3, 8. Deut. 28, 65. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Prou. 29, 25. Iſai. 57, 20. Hab. 2, 4. Iam. 2, 19.</note> trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, Phil. 2, 12. And this is the true ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his calling and election ſure vnto his own hart &amp; ſoule, as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> willeth, 2 Pet. 1, 10, which elſe is vndoubtedlie ſure vnder the Kings broad ſeale with God, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifieth, 2 Tim. 2, 19. It is moſt certaine therefore, which the Apoſtle ſaith, that we are ingrafted by baptiſme with Chriſt to the ſimilitude of his death and reſurrection, knowing that our old ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (that is, the works which by nature we haue drawen from ſinfull <hi>Adam</hi>) is cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with Chriſt, that the courſe &amp; reigne of ſinne in our mortall bodies might be deſtroied, ſeing we are dead with Chriſt, as touching ſinne (as our dipping in the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:28175:28"/> water of Baptiſme ſignifieth) but are ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen againe to a newneſſe of life vnto God in Ieſus Chriſt (as our taking vp againe from the ſame water preſenteth) giuing our bodies as inſtruments and ſeruants of righteouſneſſe and holineſſe of life, Rom. 6, 5 &amp;c. For our Lord Ieſus hath therfore redeemed vs with his moſt precious bloud from that dreadfull and damnable ſtate, wherein our father <hi>Adam</hi> was, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he fled to the trees for a vaine couert from the Lords preſence in Paradiſe, that we now being deliuered out of the bands of Satan, and the hands of the wicked our enemies ſpirituall and corporall, might ſerue him without feare in true holineſſe, and righteouſneſſe all our life long, Luke 1. verſ. 74. 75. And not that we ſhould <note n="d" place="margin">If, when the Lord, who with a word of his mouth made heauen and earth, Pſ. 33, 6. ſhall likewiſe with his word raiſe vp the dead out of their graues at the laſt day, Ioh. 5, 28<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> none will thinke that they haue any po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in that worke to quicken them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: why in our ſpirituall riſing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne, wherein we were dead, Eph. 2, 1. when hee ſayth vnto vs, Awake thou that ſleepeſt and ſtand vp from the dead, &amp; Chriſt ſhall giue thee light, Eph. 5, 14. Should we once dreame that we are helpers with Gods grace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for our ſufficiencie is of God, 2 Cor. 3, 5. who worketh in vs both the will and the deed, euen of his good pleaſure, Phi. 2, 13. And kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth vs by his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer through faith vnto ſaluation. 1 Pet. 1, 5. read Rom. 8, 30. &amp; 9, 16. See S. Pauls concluſion, Rom. 3, 28. where he oppoſeth faith to the whole law, verſ. 21, 12. and 4, 13, &amp;c. Read Phil. 3. verſ. 6. 9. and Gallat. 3. verſ. 11, 12. Iohn, 17. Tit. 3, 5.</note> merit any thing of our ſaluation by our works (as thoſe Marchants teach) and ſo deny the Lord that bought vs; for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue done all thoſe things, which are commanded vs, we are vnprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and haue done but that, which was our dutie to do, Luk. 17, 10. for Ieſus
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:28175:28"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hriſt alone hath made vs his peculiar <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eople, and ſheepe of his paſture, and not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e our ſelues, Pſal. 100, 3. And as all were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ead in <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion, ſo Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ied to redeeme all, that they which liue, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould not henceforth liue vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elues (as they did in ignorance before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir calling, Rom. 6, 19. Tit. 3. 3. 1 Pet. 1, 4) but vnto him which died for them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd roſe againe, 2 Cor. 5, 15: who his own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elfe alone hath trodden the wine-preſſe of the bloodie furie of all our ſpirituall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emies, Sathan, ſin, hell, death &amp;c. for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſcue of his church, and redemption of his people, euen by the might of his own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rme, without any helper, Iſai. 59, 16, and 63. verſ. 3, 5. Heb. 1, 3. and freely bought out our tranſgreſſions by his bitter paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and purchaſed for vs Gods euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting fauour again, and that vnſpeakeably more aboundant, Ioh. 10, 10. Rom. 5, 17. and 8, 17, and more ſure, 1 Pet. 1. ver. 3. 4. 5. (through the ſame his obedient ſufferings for vs, Phil. 2, 8. Hebr. 5, 8) then euer had <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> in his innocent roialty. Good works then ſerue to many excellent purpoſes, but cheefly to the glory of God, as our
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:28175:29"/> Lord commandeth, Mat. 5, 16. And they ſo teſtifying our faith and obedience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God in the ſight of men, do iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie vs before men, as S. <hi>Iames</hi> witneſſeth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Iam. 2. ver. 22. 23. 24.</p>
            <p>Thus haue we ſeene that Ieſus Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">Act. 4, 12. &amp; 15, 11. 1. Pet. 1, 20. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ioh. 5, 11. Heb. 11, 2. &amp;c.</note> is the only, and all ſufficient means ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of God, before the foundation of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> world, for the only ſaluation of the holy Patriarkes and Prophets, and of all men euen from <hi>Adam,</hi> in all ages, as wel before the comming of Chriſt in the fleſh, as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to the worlds end: ſo that the ſaying of the Apoſtle is clearly verefied: Ieſus Chriſt yeſterday and to day, the ſame alſo is for euer, Heb. 13, 8. Hereby likewiſe we ſee, that their purgatorie is but the<note place="margin">Purgatorie.</note> Popes painted fire, and is not in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as alſo no one point of poperie is, &amp; therefore all ſinfull. And for Purgatorie, it was deuiſed of the heathen Atheiſts long before the daies of any Pope, within the compaſſe of thoſe 1864 yeres, wherin we ſayd that <hi>Abraham</hi> and his poſteritie were ſeparate from the Gentiles, which ſpace the Apoſtle calleth the Times-paſt, wherein God ſuffered the Gentiles to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:28175:29"/> walke in their own waies, Act. 14, 16. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herein, after a ſort, the Lord hid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lfe from them, as Iſai ſpeaketh 45, 15, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntrariwiſe the ſame Prophet foretold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at the Lord would diſcouer his holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me in the ſight of all the Gentiles, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ends of the world might ſee the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation of God, 52, 10. Of thoſe Heathen (I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay) and in that time, a kind of Purgatorie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as inuented by their vaine Poets and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hiloſophers (who were the diuines of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Heathen) as in the writings of <hi>Plat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd <hi>Virgil</hi> it appeareth, from whom theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orthy marchants (for faile of ſcripture) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue coſoningly gathered the dead coles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f their Purgatory, &amp; blown vp the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o vehemently with the boiſtrous belows <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f their own hot burning breath) that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue made it nothing leſſe, if not much more) terrible, for the time, then hell it ſelf. A diueliſh deuiſe meerly forged of theſe merchants, wherby (as alſo by their maſſe) they made merchandiſe of mens ſoules, as <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> foretold vs. Yet is there a double Purgatorie, or purgation of Chriſtians in this life: The one is, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are cleanſed from all our ſinnes by
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:28175:30"/> the blood of Ieſus chriſt, Heb. 1, 3. 1 Ioh. 1, 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Reuel. 1, 5 which vvas alſo ſignified vnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the law by that blood offered, Leuit. 17, 11, vvhich ſee how the Apoſtle interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth 1 Hebr. 10, 1 &amp;c. For almoſt al thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvere by the law purged vvith blood, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvithout ſhedding of blood is no remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Heb. 9, 22. This our firſt purgation is figured alſo by baptiſme, where our wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing in the vvater (or new birth, Tit. 3. 5) betokeneth our putting on of Chriſt, Gal. 3, 27. vvhich in the Reuelation is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the vvhite raiment<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Reuel. 3, verſ. 4. 18, and is named of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> the new man, vvhich after God is created in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and true holineſſe, Eph 4, 24, which is to mortifie the deedes of the body by the ſpirit, Rom. 8, 13, and to put off the ſinfull body of the fleſh, Col. 2, 11, that is, to crucifie our old man, that the body of ſin might be deſtroied, that henceforth vve ſhould not ſerue ſin, Rom. 6, 6, for they that are Chriſts, haue crucified the fleſh vvith the affections and luſts, Gal. 5, 24. read Col. 3, 5, and Tit. 2, verſ. 11. 12 &amp;c. Our other purgation is by the fire of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and perſecutions, Dan. 12, 10,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:28175:30"/> which all that will liue godly in Chriſt Ieſus muſt indure, Pſal. 34, 19. Phil. 1, 29. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Tim. 4, 10. 2 Tim. 3, 12. 1 Pet. 1, ver 6. 7: <q>that the triall of our fayth being much more precious then gold, that periſheth (though it be tried by fire) might be ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnto our praiſe and honour, and glory at the appearing of Ieſus Chriſt, whom wee haue not ſeene, and yet loue him; in whom now though we ſee him not, yet do we beleeue and reioice vvith ioy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable and glorious, receauing the end of our faith, euen the ſaluation of our ſoules,</q> 1 Pet. 1. ver. 7, 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9, for if we be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the corrections whereof all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful are partakers, then are we baſtards and not ſonnes, Hebr. 12, 8. And here wee may ſee that <hi>Bildad</hi> argued very abſurdly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Iob,</hi> in reaſoning thus: If thou wert righteous, God would not afflict thee, but he afflicteth thee, therefore art thou vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous, <hi>Iob</hi> 8. ver. 6. 20. Wherefore <hi>Iob</hi> confuteth this abſurditie in the next chapter, verſ. 21. 22. Theſe afflictions of the faithfull were moſt liuely repreſented by the beaſts diuided in the middeſt, in the couenant that God made with <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:28175:31"/> where the foules fell vpon the carkaſes, &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Lorde went betweene thoſe diuide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> peeces of the beaſtes with a ſmoking for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace and firebrand, Gen. 15. verſe 10. 11. 17. to teach <hi>Abraham</hi> that his poſterity ſhuld ſuffer many and diuerſe afflictions, to be rent and torne in peeces, &amp; tried with fire &amp; fagot, as the lord there in a word plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſeth, verſe 13. Exod. 2, 11. Heb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> verſe 36. 37. In the law likewiſe this was prefigured, where they were commanded in all their oblations to offer ſalt, Leuit 2, 13. which Chriſt himſelfe thus enterpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: Euerie man ſhall be ſalted with fire, and euerie ſacriſice ſhal be ſalted with ſalt, Marke 9, 49. This ſacrifice is euerie Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian mans bodie, which he is bound of dutie and ſeruice (euen by reaſon Rom. 6, 19.) to giue vp, and offer holie and acceptable vnto God, Ro. 12, 1. for to this end our ſauiour ſaith to all: If any man wil come after me, let him denie himſelfe, and take vp his croſſe daily, and follow me, Luke 9, 23. I am loth to be longer in this point, yet ſince we are come thus farre in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the field of Chriſtian combats, let vs at the leaſt take a ſuruey of the battell: for it
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:28175:31"/> may be though we comenow but only to ſee the hoſt, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did, 1 Sam. 17. verſ. 17. 20. that the Lord will one day call vs forth as he did <hi>Dauid,</hi> to fight againſt Goliath, verſe 49 &amp;c. For howſoeuer worldlie ſouldiers are diſcharged either for infirmities, or age: yet none are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from this chriſtian warfare, but all (euen from children, Mat. 19, 14) that feare God, muſt prepare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to this warefare, which is not againſt fleſh, and <q>bloud, but againſt principalities, againſt powers, againſt worldly gouerners, the princes of the darkneſſe of this world, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſpiritual wickedneſſes,</q> which are in the hie places, Eph. 6, 12. The weapons of this warfare are the verie whole armoure of god, Eph. 6, 11 &amp;c. by which Chriſt our Captaine hath alreadie conquered all the power and kingdome of Sathan for vs, Iſai. 59. verſ. 16. 17. 18. Wherefore Saint <hi>Paule</hi> as an Heralt about to crie an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arme in this great hoſt, biddeth vs to be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might, Eph. 6, 10. And to watch, ſtand faſt in the faith, to quit vs like men, and be ſtrong, 1 Cor. 10, 13. And he ſheweth
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:28175:32"/> the meanes how we may ſo do, namelie by continuing in one ſpirit, and in one mind, fighting together through the faith of the Goſpel, Philip. 1, 27. S. <hi>Iohn</hi> alſo (to comfort vs) before we haue giuen one ſtroke, telleth vs that we haue alreadie gotten the victorie, and ouercome the wicked one, that is the Deuil, 1 Ioh. 2, 13. This might ſeeme vnto vs a paradox, but that we cannot forget our grand captaine Chriſt, the head of his bodie the Church, Col. 1, 18. who hath ſpoiled the principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, &amp; powers, and triumphed ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his croſſe, Col. 2, 15. and ſo caſt out the prince of this world, Ioh. 12, 31. &amp; ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the world, Ioh. 16, 33. Thus there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore againſt Satan, and his kingdome, with all our ſpirituall enemies, being firſt ſubdued by Chriſt, we are ſet to fight that we might be moſt ſure of the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſeeing our Captaine hath giuen them their deaths wound. Wherefore now if we do but reſiſt the Deuill (in a ſtedfaſt faith, as <hi>S. Peter</hi> aduiſeth, 1 Pet. 5, 9) he will flie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, Iam. 4, 7. We ſee then that Chriſt our Captain dealeth with vs in this chriſtian fight, as
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:28175:32"/> Captaine <hi>Ioſhua</hi> did with the chiefe war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iers of Iſraell in the Lords battell againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Amorits, who cauſing the 5. Kings of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Amorits to be brought out vnto him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orth of the caue at Makkedah, where for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eare they had hid themſelues, ſaid vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he chiefe of the men of war, which went with him: Come nere, ſet your feet vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he neckes of theſe kinges &amp;c. feare not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or be faint-hearted, but be ſtrong: for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hus wil the Lord do to all your enemies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gainſt whom yee fight, Ioſh. 10. verſ 24. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>5. And though we be able to do all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hings through the help of Chriſt, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>trengthneth vs, Phil. 4, 13. for it is he, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat ſhall tread downe our enemies, Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 8, 13. yet whatſoeuer faileth in vs to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erforme againſt our ſpirituall aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies, that Chriſt himſelfe moſt tenderlie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffecteth for vs, as good Captaine <hi>Gide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> did touching thoſe kinges of <hi>Midia, Zebah</hi> and <hi>Zalmunna,</hi> againſt whom <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her</hi> his eldeſt ſonne durſt not draw his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, Iud 8, 20. yea we ſhall walke vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he lion and the aſpe, the yong lion and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he dragon ſhall we tread vnder feete, Pſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>1, 13. for euen like as in olde time Chriſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:28175:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> was the Captaine and guide vnto the Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raelites to conduct them ſafely throug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the great and terrible wilderneſſe in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> borders of <hi>Moab,</hi> wherein were fier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſerpents, &amp; Scorpions, Deut. 8, 15. whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conduction (as the Prophet noteth) ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neuer to be forgotten, Iere. 2, 6. Euen ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt hath giuen vs power to treade o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſerpents and ſcorpions, and ouer all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> power of the enemie, that nothing ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hurt vs, Luk. 10, 16. Iſa. 11, 6. &amp; 65, 25. Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 2, 18. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that for Chriſts ſake we be killed all day long, &amp; counte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as ſheep for the ſlaughter: yet in all theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thinges we are more then conquerer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> through our Captaine, that loueth vs Rom. 8. verſe. 36. 37. for though we walk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the fleſh, yet we do not war after th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fleſh: for the weapons of our warfare an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not carnall, but mightie through God to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> caſt downe holdes, caſting downe the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations, and euerie high thing, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is <note n="c" place="margin">For an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple here of ſee with what violence Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans power falleth down at the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles preachings, Luk. 10, 18. Read act. 24, 26. where Paul a priſoner maketh Felix the preſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to quake.</note> exalted againſt the knowledge o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, and bringing into captiuitie eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie thought to the ordinance of Chriſt, Cor. 10. verſ. 3. 4. 5. And our Captaine is faithfull, which will not ſuffer vs to be
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:28175:33"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mpted aboue that we be able, but will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uen giue the iſſue with the tentation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat we may be able to beare it, 1 Cor. 10, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3. Therefore let vs not be afraid for any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>errour, 1 Pet. 3, 14. But as our Captaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſus, that he might ſanctiſie the people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith his owne bloud, ſuffred without the gate: euen ſo let vs go forth out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ampe, to this fight bearing his reproch, Heb. 13. verſ. 12. 13. Knowing this, that if we ſuffer with Chriſt, we ſhall alſo be glorified with him, Rom. 8, 17. &amp; though we know, that this our ſtrife againſt ſin (Hebr. 12, 4) is alway in our Captaines ſight, Pſal. 33, verſ. 18. 19. yet the more to encourage vs thereunto he telleth vs that he knoweth our tribulations. Reuel. 2, 9. for he knoweth whereof we are made, Pſ. 103, 14, and is touched with the feeling of our infirmities, becauſe his owne ſelfe was in all thinges tempted in like ſort, Hebr. 4, 15. therefore he ſupporteth vs, when we faint, and ſaith to euerie one of vs: My grace is ſufficient for thee, 2 Cor. 12, 9. feare none of thoſe thinges, which thou ſhalt ſuffer, but be thou faithful vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the death, &amp; I wil giue thee the crowne
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:28175:34"/> of life, Reuel. 2, 10.<note place="margin">Maſſe.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Their Maſſe likewiſe is moſt flatlie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt<note place="margin">Heb. 2, 17. &amp; 3, 1. &amp; 4, 14 &amp;c. &amp; 5, 5. &amp; 6, 20. &amp; 7. verſ. 16. 21. and 8, 1. and 9, 11. and 13, 12.</note> the word of God: for whereas Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is our onlie High-ſacrificer to offer and preſent vs blameleſſe in his own merits and righteouſneſſe vnto God his father, and that by offring vp his bodie on the croſſe for our ſinnes once for all, Heb. 9, 25 &amp;c. and 10. 10 &amp;c. Theſe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants haue of their owne braine deuiſed a ſtrange ſacrifice, and prieſts for the nonce, to offer it in Chriſts ſtead to God, as propitiatorie both for the quicke and dead, which contumelious blaſphemie vnto Chriſt (beſides that ſo they crucifie againe to themſelues the ſonne of God, and make a mocke of him, Heb. 6, 6) who ſeeth not to be wickedlie deuiſed of thoſe marchants to make marchandiſe of Gods people for their owne filthie lucre?</p>
            <p>And where they ſay as blaſphemouſly (for all their coſoning is blaſphemie, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel. 13. 1) that the Iewes <note n="f" place="margin">The Iewes falſlie charged by the Papiſtes.</note> haue falſified and corrupt the old Teſtament, and therefore that the doctrine thereof is doubtful, they ſpeake moſt ignorantly and vntrulie: for we haue Chriſtes word to the contrarie,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:28175:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> who ſaieth: <note n="g" place="margin">That place is otherwiſe taken: but the plaine wordes of the text waſh this crime away.</note> Verilie I ſay vnto you, till heauen and earth periſh, one iot, or one title of the law ſhall not ſcape, Mat. 5, 18. Of all the <note n="h" place="margin">The prickes which now are v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for vowels in reading that tongue, were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted 400. yeares after by the Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorites.</note> Hebrew letters of the Iewes, their jod was the leaſt, which (after the Greeke) is called a jote, and (for the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe) a little: whereby our Lord, to ſignifie the integritie of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, here warranteth vnder an oth that not euen ſo litle of the law ſhall faile. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, our Sauiour rectifying the falſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations<note place="margin">Mat. 5, 21 &amp;c. &amp; 15, 4 &amp;c.</note> of the law by the Scribes &amp; Phariſies, neuer chargeth them of alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring anie text thereof: yea rather he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth the puritie of the law, by ſending the people to the diligent reading of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and the Prophets, Mat. 23, 1 &amp;c. Luk. 10, 26. &amp; 16, 29. Iohn. 5. 39. And there is no one point of doctrine conteined in the new Teſtament, that is not alſo confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and approued by the old, Luk, 24, 44. Act. 17. verſ. 2. 3. &amp; 26, 22. 1 Cor. 15. verſ. 3. 4. And the new Teſtament is the accompliſhing and fulfilling of the olde, Mat. 5, 17. Rom. 10, 4. But as theſe Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants haue moſt falſlie belied the Iewes for the old teſtament, ſo they themſelues
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:28175:35"/> haue verie deſpitefullie <note n="i" place="margin">The Papiſtes blaſphemouſlie miſcall the holie ſcriptures, &amp; why.</note> blaſphemed the new teſtament, and holie ſcriptures (and all becauſe they tell vs how theſe iugling marchantes coſen the world) terming the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a noſe of waxe: a ſhipmans hoſe: an yn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken goſpel: to be of no better authoritie then <hi>Aeſopes</hi> fables: and moſt wickedlie cenſuring the holie Ghoſt, the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of <hi>Dauids</hi> Pſalms, with that prophane verſe:
<q>
                  <l>Scribimus indocti, docti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mat a paſſim<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Whole bookes of verſes commonlie,</l>
                  <l>Aſwell th' unlearnt, as learnt write we.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This is that Torch-blaſing-ſtar worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, which infecteth the pure waters of Gods word with his bitter blaſphemies, whereof they die that drinke it, Reuel. 8, 11. refuſing the waters of life, Iohn. 4, 10. Therefore turne away from ſuch, ſaith the holie ghoſt, 2 Tim. 3, 5. And, go out of her, my people, that you be not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers in her ſinnes, and that yee receiue not of her plagues, Reuel. 18, 4.</p>
            <p>And here becauſe we are come to S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Reuelation, which contemeth a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall prophecie of all the afflictions (ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and particular) that the Church of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:28175:35"/> Chriſt ſhall endure till the laſt day, and by moſt euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t tokens pointeth at Rome, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence thoſe euils ſhould iſſue: let vs giue the Catholiks a taſt of that their fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie cage, Reuel. 18, 2) by viewing the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe of Gods ſcourge among the<note place="margin">Rome.</note> wicked. The <note n="k" place="margin">Nimrod, Cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s nephew, built Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, and Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve of the Aſſyria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, by which two countries Gods church of the Iewes indured manie times moſt cruell tyrannie, &amp; at length miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble captiuitie: Iſrael by the Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, anno mundi. 3264. 2 King. 17, 6. and 122. yeares after Iudah by the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonians, ibid. 24. 10 &amp;c. Ier 50, 17. wherefore the Lord aſſureth his church to be eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciallie reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged of theſe two, Mic. 5, 6.</note> Babylonians, the moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient afflicters of the church of God, Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 10. verſe 8, 10) hauing a long time tiran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized in the world, at length, by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God, grew to ſuch an head, that they ouercame manie and mightie nations, Ierem. 25 &amp; 27) in ſo much that they preſumed, and preuailed againſt the Lords people, leading them away cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, and deſtroying their citie and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in reuenge whereof, they were van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed of the Medes and Perſians, Iere. 50, 28. &amp; 51, 11. Dan. 5, verſ. 30. 31. The Macedonians ſubdued the Medes &amp; Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, Dan. 7, 6. and 8. verſ. 5. 6. 7. 20. 21. The Seleucians, or Aſians, ſuppreſſed the Macedonians, Dan. 7, 7. The Romanes foiled the Seleucians, Dan. 11. verſ. 30. 44. Finallie, the Romanes by litle and litle through mutuall diſſention and ciuil diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord hauing altered and diminiſhed their
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:28175:36"/> owne ſtate, firſt begin to perſecute Chriſt in his ſwadlings &amp; infancie, forcing him to be layd in a manger, Luke 2, 7. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they moſt vniuſtly exacted Tribute of him being the great kings ſonne, and therefore free, Matth. 17, 24 &amp;c. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they condemned him to death, Matth. 20, 19. Iohn. 11, 48 &amp; 18, 35. &amp; 19, 15. Act. 4, 27. Reuel. 11, 8. And laſtly, they <note n="l" place="margin">This notable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, as well for the auncient pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie ſo long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as for ſome future &amp; ſtraunge euent, our Lord him ſelfe aduiſeth vs euerie one to conſider, Mat. 24, 15.</note> deſtroyed the Citie and Temple, Dan. 9. 26. Luke 21, 20, as the Babylonians had done before, and why ſhall they not haue the Babylonians reward, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vtter deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for the ſame? Read Zech. 14. ve. 1. 2. 3. The holy Ghoſt calleth this ougly cage and curſed citie Rome, for the filthineſſe thereof, Sodome: and for her crueltie to Chriſts Saints, Egypt: and in reſpect of <hi>Pilate</hi> the Roman Deputie that deliuered Chriſt to death, Ioh. 19. verſ. 15. 16, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it the place where our Lord was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, Reu. 11, 8. And euen like as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Babilo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in the Eaſt parts of the world moſt cruelly afflicted Gods people the Iewes, Iſa. 47, 6. Ier. 50, 17: ſo this Citie in the Weſt S. <hi>Iohn</hi> calleth Babylon, Reu. 16, 19. &amp; 18, 2 &amp;c. which (by the ſpirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie)
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:28175:36"/> he ſaw ſhould no leſſe cruelly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the Saints &amp; ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Chriſt. And for this ſimilitude of Rome with Babylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, S. <hi>Iohn</hi> calleth Rome, or rather Antichriſt the king of that Antichriſtian vſurpatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Iſa. 21, 2. Iere. 51, 25.</note> by the Hebrue word <hi>abaddon</hi> (deſtroyer, Reu. 9, 11) as the prophets <hi>Iſay</hi> &amp; <hi>Ieremy</hi> had many hundred years before called old Babylon, &amp; the king therof. And becauſe <hi>John</hi> wrot to the Greek churches of <note n="m" place="margin">This was Aſia minor, where Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſons inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, among whom S. Paule had long before this time planted the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, Act. 19. verſ. <hi>r.</hi> 10. 26. &amp; 20, 18 &amp;c And were thus through pietie per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwaded to dwel in the Tents of Sem. Gen. 9, 29. as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for pollicie they were perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded 500 years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to dwell, and confederate with Sem againſt Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, Iſai. 21, 2. Gen. 10. verſ. 2. 22. Antichriſts cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racterie name.</note> Aſia, Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 4 he interpreteth the hebrue in their own tong, <hi>Apollyon</hi> (deſtroyer) as S. <hi>Paule</hi> likewiſe calleth him the ſon of perdition, or deſtruction, 2 Theſ. 2, 3. And S. <hi>Peter</hi> reſpecting their whole corporation, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth them, priuy-inbringers of the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of deſtruction, 2. Pet. 2, 1. Wherefore <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> or ſome graue father in that age, haue wiſely (as the holy Ghoſt aduiſed, Reu. 13, 18) gathered his characterie name of the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, both which exactly containe that number (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) 666, the Beaſtes name: the former noting Rome, the Citie, and language of Antichriſt; the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Italie, his peculiar Church and countreye. VVhich Citie, the Angell telleth <hi>Iohn</hi> is built vpon ſeuen moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:28175:37"/> Reuel. 17. verſ. 9. 18. As alſo <hi>Virgil,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Georg. 2. 1 Triſt. El. 4 &amp; 3, 7.</note> and moſt plainly <hi>Ouid</hi> (more then once) doth witneſſe Rome to be:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Sed, quae de ſeptem totum circumſpicit orbem</l>
               <l>Montibus, imperij, Roma, deumque lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>My home is Rome imperiall, the place of gods no doubt:</l>
                  <l>Which from ſeuen mountains doth behold the whole world round about.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>This Romiſh Babylon, &amp; papall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration S. <hi>Iohn</hi> calleth not a Virgin (as yet the Prophet Iſai named old Babylon, Iſai. 47, 1) but an abhominable who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh woman, who, for her filthie <note n="n" place="margin">Becauſe Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt muſt ſit in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of God, (i. preſume autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie ouer matters of Chriſtian faith &amp; religion, 2 Theſ. 2, 4) And haue a ſhew of godlines, 2 Tim. 3, 5. the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſpirit, to helpe our infirmities, ſpeaking euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly (as S. Paul teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, 1 Tim. 4, 1. which S. Iohn cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth ſpirituallie, Reuel. 11, 8) lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out in open &amp; plaine termes the name, Myſterie, written in the forehead of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, calling it Great Babylon, the mother of whoredomes and abominations of the earth. Re. 17. 5</note> forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and whoredomes, far more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure then Babylon, was far vnfit for ſo puer a name. Reuel. 17. verſ. 3. 5. He deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth her coulers to be purple and <note n="o" place="margin">The Pope can be content to weare Chriſtes ſka<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>let robe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (howſoeuer it was put vpon Chriſt in mocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie) it repreſented a kinglie maieſty, Mat 27, 28. but yet he will haue it alſo adorned with golde, precious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ones, &amp; pearles, that ſo it may be the true liuerie of Antichriſt. Reuel. 17, 4.</note> ſkar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, as the Pope himſelfe, and his Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals euen at this day vſe to weare, Reuel. 17, 4. And finallie, to remoue all doubt of that cruell citie, the Angel certifieth <hi>Iohn</hi> that it is that great citie which ruleth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the kings of the earth, which then,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:28175:37"/> when S. <hi>Iohn</hi> wrote that Reuellation, was Rome, Reu. 17, 18. And that in it (that is, within the far &amp; wide vſurped power &amp; iuriſdiction thereof) was found the bloud of all the Prophets and Saintes, that were ſlaine vpon the earth, Reuel. 18, 24. No maruell then, if the Romanes, beginning ſo cruellie with Chriſt, and ioining with the Iewes to crucifie the Lord of glorie, hold on ſtil in all impious and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous rage againſt the true chriſtians: and, being abſurde and reprobate in doctrine concerning the faith, be derided, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted of all good men, whom Chriſts ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants ſhall at length vanquiſh moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſlie, and reward them double accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their workes. The ſpirit of God hath commaunded ſo, and we are ſure it will be ſo, and haue good hope to ſee it ſo Reuel. 18, 6. for their great city (that is, their former large vſurped power ouer manie countries and nations) is alreadie diuided into three partes, Reuel. 16, 19: for of that large Romiſh corporation ſome nations are become true Chriſtian prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, as, England, Scotland, Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, Denmarke &amp;c. ſome hold ſtill the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:28175:38"/> Romiſh religion, as: Italie, Spaine, and the countries vnder their tyrannie; ſome are neither, as the kingdomes and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries won from Antichriſt by the Turke, Reuel. 9, verſe 14. 15. 20. with all other Atheiſts &amp; Sectaries among the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſorts. The Lord hath graciouſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun their ruine in diuerſe of thoſe tenne kingdomes, which ſometime wholly bent their power to aſſiſt the Beaſt, Reue. 17. verſe 12. 13: but now a good part of them forſake and hate the Beaſt, Reu. 17. verſe 16. 17. And, as we haue heard that thoſe deuilliſh ſpirits are gone forth vnto the kings of the earth to gather them (in their holy League, as they call it) to the battell of the great day (for their vſuall ſpeech is, that they hope for a day, but the holy Ghoſt ſaith) of God almighty: ſo we looke when they ſhal be gathered (as bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God, we ſaw a faire beginning in the yeare 1588, when they compaſſed the <note n="p" place="margin">With ſuch glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tles it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Lord to beautifie the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſors of his word as Da. 7, 18 &amp; 8. v. 10. 24. &amp; P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 105, 15.</note> Tents of the Saints about, &amp; the beloued Citie, Reuel. 20, 9) at <note n="q" place="margin">S. Iohn ſetting down Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>naged<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, addeth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that it is ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Hebrewe, wherby he would haue vs to ſearch the old Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the true ſenſe &amp; meaning of the ſtorie: &amp; ſo much alſo he meant by Abaddon before, in which word he expreſſeth the Prophets therun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to alledged, para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſtically, the more to ſtir vp our deſire in ſeeking out the truth.</note> Ar-mageddon, Reuelat. 16, 16. For Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> alluding to Magiddon, or Mageddon, which was a region in Iudaea towards the mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rane
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:28175:38"/> ſea in the tribe of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> calleth it Ar-mageddon (the mountaine of the ſlaine) and of purpoſe addeth Ar (moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine) to Mageddon, becauſe of mount Tabor, which being ſtrongly enuironed with other neare mountaines, Ier. 46, 18, was within the coaſt of Mageddon, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Barak</hi> and <hi>Debora,</hi> with their armie, expecting the comming of <hi>Siſera,</hi> moſt wonderfully diſcomfited king <hi>Iabin,</hi> and his complices, the maine Reliques of the Canaanites, and moſt deſpitefull enemies of Gods Church, Iudg. 4. verſe 6. 12. 15. &amp; 5. verſe 18. 19. Pſal. 83. verſe 9. 10.</p>
            <p>In that Mageddon alſo at the brooke Kiſhon <hi>Elias</hi> ſlue the idolatrous Prophets of <hi>Baal,</hi> 1. King. 18, 40. The holy Ghoſt therefore, leading vs to that place and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie, would put vs in moſt certaine hope and expectation of the like, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie rare victories of the idolatrous Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes, the ſworne aduerſaries of the true Church of Chriſt. And, for confirmation of this Truth, <hi>Debora,</hi> by the power of the ſpirit, winding in all Gods aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries together on an heape, concludeth her Epinice or ſong of her triumph with
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:28175:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> this acclamation: ſo let all thine enemies periſh, ô Lord. Amen. read Pſalm. 83.</p>
            <p>Thus haue we brieflie ſeene how the Lord God, being before all beginning, &amp;<note place="margin">Pſal. 90, 2.</note> from euerlaſting hath by his wonderful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> workmanſhip of the world, declared his eternall power and Godhead vnto men, creating all things for the benefit of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and man himſelfe to feare and loue the Lord: who, being created in holie inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, and made the ſoueraigne of all earthlie creatures, wittingly, and wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie tranſgreſſed the commaundement of his Lord, whereby he moſt iuſtlie procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red eternall death to himſelfe, and to all his poſteritie. But the Lord vnſpeakably rich in mercie, found out a Redeemer, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of the ſeede of the woman, the Man Ieſus Chriſt the righteous, the verie ſon of God, who, after manie promiſes of his comming in ſundrie ages, when the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of time was come, being miraculouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie conceiued by the holie Ghoſt, in the wombe of a virgin, became man, to ſuffer for man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that death, which all man-kind had rightly deſerued, and ſo both freeing vs from the puniſhment of ſinne, and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:28175:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> clearing vs from the guiltineſſe thereof, hath ſet vs at peace againe with God, and purchaſed an inheritance immortall and vndefiled, and that fadeth not away, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued for vs in heauen, and not commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted anie more to our owne keeping (as it was to <hi>Adams</hi>) for the Lord himſelfe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaineth our lot, Pſal. 16, 5. and keepeth vs by his power through faith vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, which is prepared to be ſhewed in the laſt time, 1. Pet. 1, 4. requiring of vs that we ſhould not nowe liue vnto our ſelues, but vnto him, that died for vs, and roſe againe, that we likewiſe ſhould riſe to a newneſſe of life in holineſſe, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and Chriſtian ſobrietie in this preſent world, looking for the bleſſed <note n="q" place="margin">This is the true marke of all the godly and faithful generally, both vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; the new, a ſecure hope and expectation of the laſt iudgement in the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt, Luc. 12, 36. &amp; 21, 28. Phil. 3, 20. 1 Th. 1. ver. 3. 10. 2 Theſ. 3, 5. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 9, 28. and 11, 3. Iam. 5, 8. Re, 22, 20.</note> hope, and appearance of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, to euerlaſting life.</p>
            <p>Reſolue now thy ſelfe, Chriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, reſigne all earthly <note n="r" place="margin">Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ought by the counſell of the holy Ghoſt, to examine &amp; proue them ſelues whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be in the faith, &amp; feele the ſpirite of Chriſt working in them, 2 Cor. 13, 5: for by Chriſts ſpirit of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption (which is a witneſſe in our hearts that we are the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god 1 Ioh. 5, 10. Rom, 8. ve. 9. 15. Eph. 1, 13) we delight in the law of God, &amp; take no pleaſure in ſin, Heb. 11. 25. but are grieued with ſin, 2. Pet. 2, 8. and ſay with S. Paul: I do not the good thing, which I would but the euil, which I would not, Rom. 8, 19. And euery one, whoſe heart and conſcience can truly thus perſwade him, is vndoubtedly the elected child of God. Where contrarily, the reprobate delite in ſin, becauſe they are of the world, Ioh. 8, 23. &amp; therfore loue the world, Ioh. 15, 19. &amp; the things of the world, as the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and pride of life. 1 Ioh. 2. v. 15. 16. And ſhal receiue the wages of vnrighteouſneſſe, as they which count it pleaſure to liue delitiouſly for a ſeaſon, 2 Pet. 2, 13.</note> affections, Col. 3,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:28175:40"/> 2. and conſult no longer with fleſh and blood, but enter into counſell with thine owne ſoule for the apprehending of this eternall life: which life, for the maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous excellencie thereof (being that hid treaſure, that precious pearle, Matth. 13. verſe 44. 46) can not be ſufficiently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by all the glory of the world. The holy Ghoſt chuſing out the moſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things that nature can affoord, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe vnto vs the heauenly Ieruſalem, our euerlaſting citie, ſaith thus: The citie was <q>pure gold, like cleare glaſſe, the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the wall thereof were garniſhed with all maner of precious ſtones, the gates of perle, the ſtreets of pure gold &amp;c. It needeth neither Sunne, nor Moone to ſhine in it, for the glorie of God did light it. The people which are ſaued ſhal walk in the light of it, &amp; the kings of the earth ſhall bring their glorie and honour vnto it,</q> Reu. 21, 18 &amp;c. O how excellent things are ſpoken of thee, thou citie of God, Pſa. 87, 2. The eye hath not ſeene, nor the eare heard, neither came into mans heart the glorious things, which God hath prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for them that loue him, 1. Cor. 2, 9.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:28175:40"/> Theſe maruellous things (as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith) the Angels deſired to prie into, 1 Pet. 1, 12. For, indeede, the Angels recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued firſt knowledge of Gods eternal wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and purpoſe in Chriſt, concerning theſe things, by the Church, Ephſ. 3, 10. And euery creature with feruent deſire wayteth when the ſonnes of God ſhall be reuealed, Rom. 8, 19, &amp; ſhine as the ſunne, in the kingdome of their father. Mat. 13, 43. For although we be now the ſonnes of God by faith in Chriſt Ieſus, Gal. 3, 26: yet doth it not now appeare what we ſhal be, 1 Ioh. 3, 2. becauſe that through Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian mortification, 2 Cor. 4. verſe 10. 11. and 5, 15. wee are in this world as dead, and our life is hid with Chriſt in God: but when Chriſt, which is our life, ſhall appeare, then ſhall we alſo appeare with him in glorie, Col. 3, 3 &amp;c. For the Lord Ieſus Chriſt ſhall chaunge our vile bodie, that it may be faſhioned like vnto his glorious bodie, Phil. 3, 21. and then we ſhall ſee him as he is, 1 Ioh. 3, 2. <hi>Moſes</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mount Horeb ſawe but ſome glimſe of the ſhadowed maieſtie of God (for elſe no man hath ſeene God in his eſſentiall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:28175:41"/> at anie time, Ioh. 1, 18) and the skin of his face ſo ſhone withall, that neither the Iſraelites, nor <hi>Aaron</hi> him ſelfe, were able to looke vpon him, vntil he had put a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour ouer his face, Exod. 34, 29 &amp;c. <hi>Elias</hi> alſo vpon the ſame mount, at Gods viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble preſence, couered his face with his mantell, 1 King. 19. verſe 8. 13. And of all other <hi>Moſes</hi> was once ſo hardie, that he deſired the Lord to ſhew him his very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine maieſtie, but that requeſt obtained would haue coſt him his life, and in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie therefore it was denied him, Exod. 33, 18 &amp;c. But what ſpeake we of mans diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie in this behalfe? Neither the Angels them ſelues are able to behold the Lord in his full maieſtie, nor men to endure euen the ſight of an angel, as we ſee prefigured by the face and feeet-couering in Iſayes viſion, Iſa. 6, 2. Seeing then, after this life, we ſhall alway haue the fruition of this excellent and heauenly glorie, which now neither men, nor Angels can ſuſtaine, not vpon an earthly mountaine in a material Tabernacle with <hi>Peter,</hi> Mat. 17, 4: but in Heauen, in that precious and heauenly Ieruſalem, Heb. 12, 22. with God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:28175:41"/> the Sonne, and the holy Spirit, that moſt bleſſed and glorious Trinitie, in whoſe preſence is the fulneſſe of ioy, and at whoſe right hand there are pleaſures for euermore, Pſal. 16, 11. together with all the goodly companie of Angels, Zech. 3, 7. Heb. 12, 22. and holy Saintes, Mat. 8, 11. ſeeing (I ſay) we looke for new hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens and a new earth, according to his promiſe, wherein dwelleth righteouſnes, 2. Pet. 3, 13. and for ſuch a kingdome, Luk. 12, 32. for he is faithfull that hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, Hebr. 10, 23. what manner perſons ought we to be in holy conuerſation and godlineſſe, looking for, and haſting vnto the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of the great day of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt to iudgement, giuing diligence that we may be found in him in peace without ſpot and blameles? 2. Pet. 3, 11 &amp;c. And in the meane time, let Moſes ſhewe vs the ſhortnes of this life, Pſal. 90, 10. And that couetous foole in S. Luke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> teach vs that the incerteinty ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is more daungerous then the ſhortnes, Luk. 12, 20. let vs vſe this world as though we vſed it not, 1. Cor. 7, 31, for the faſhion thereof is as chaungable as our garment,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:28175:42"/> Pſal. 102, 26. Let the holy ghoſt perſwade vs to carie our ſelues without couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and to be content with thoſe thinges,<note place="margin">Reade Mat. 6, 25 &amp;c. and Pſal. 37.</note> which we haue: for he hath ſaid, I will <q>not faile thee, neither forſake thee, ſo that we may boldly ſay, The Lord is my hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, neither will I feare what man can do vnto me,</q> Heb. 13. verſe 5. 6. And for our continuall &amp; aſſured hope of the glorious life to come, let vs reioyce in the Lord al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, Philip. 4, 4. <q>Let vs caſt away euery thing that preſſeth downe, and the ſinne, that hangeth ſo faſt on: let vs runne with pacience the race that is ſet before vs, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vnto Ieſus the author &amp; finiſher of our faith, who for the ioy, that was ſet before him, endured the croſſe, deſpiſed ſhame, and is ſet at the right hand of the throne of God, Hebr. 12. verſe 1. 2.</q> This Ieſus, being the fore-runner for vs, is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into heauen, Hebr. 6, 20. and gone to prepare a place for vs, Ioh. 14, 2. where we haue alreadie an intereſt by Chriſt our head, as hauing our conuerſation with him in heauen, from whence we looke for the ſauiour, euen our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, Phil. 3, 20. Who ſhall then ſeparate vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:28175:42"/> the loue of Chriſt? ſhal tribulation, or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, or perſecution, or famine, or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, or perill, or ſword? much leſſe (I hope) ſhall the loue of the world, wife, children, friends, honour, &amp;c. remoue vs from this our eternall glorie: perſwaded that neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor any creature ſhall be able to ſeparate vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord, Rom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 8, 35 &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To conclude, courteous Reader, if thou beeſt affected to the Romiſh religion (as haply thou mighteſt through the decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable ſhew of theſe marchants counterfet godlineſſe) I charge thee before God, and his elect Angels, that thou dearely tender the ſaluation of thy ſoule, which Chriſt hath purchaſed with his owne blood, and that thou ſettle and ground the certainty of thy ſaluation vpon the written word of God (and not on the vncertaine Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of thoſe crafty marchants) with full aſſurance of faith firmely ſtayed in Gods promiſes through hope, as the ſure anker of the ſoule: for ſo the Scriptures plentifully teach, Pſal. 56, 11. Ro, 8, 38 &amp;c.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:28175:43"/> Col. 2, 2. Heb. 6, 19. and 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. verſe 22. 23.</p>
            <p>The word of God is the only rule of a Chriſtians life, Pſal. 119, 9. There will no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe ſted vs at the laſt day, when we muſt all appeare before the tribunal ſeate of Chriſt, 2 Cor. 5, 10) but Gods own word &amp; promiſe. He wil allow of nothing, but that which himſelf hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded, Deut. 12, 32. for all other things (be they neuer ſo glorious in the ſight of men) the Lord will anſwer, Who required this at your hands, Iſa. 1, 12. Ier. 7. verſ. 22. 23. Seek ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the Bible, &amp; booke of the Lord, &amp; reade Iſa. 34, 16: for, Bleſſed is he that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, &amp; they that heare the word of God, and keepe it, Luke 11, 28. Reu. 1, 3. You know whither <hi>Abraham</hi> ſent the richma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s brethren: namely to <note n="r" place="margin">Albeit the Law of Moſes, and the Prophetes were red euery ſabbath day in the Iewes ſynagoges, yet did they not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them, act. 13, 27. &amp; that becauſe they did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue them, Ioh. 5, 46. which their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe ſee how S. Paule ſaith was foreſhadowed by Moſes vaile, 2. Co. 3. 13 &amp;c. read Heb. 4, 2.</note> reade <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; the Prophets, that ſo they might be warned to auoid hel flames, Luke 16, 27 &amp;c. Our Lord told thoſe Phariſies, that in vaine they worſhipped God, teaching for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, mens precepts, Mat. 15, 9. He told thoſe Sadduces alſo that they were decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, becauſe they knew not the ſcriptures, Mat. 22, 29. Remember Saint <hi>Paules</hi> war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Let no man deceiue you with vaine
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:28175:43"/> words: for through ſuch things commeth the wrath of God vpon the children of diſobedience, be not therefore compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with them, Epheſ. 5, 6 &amp;c. And that fierce wrath of god, in puniſhing the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of his word, the Apoſtle declareth to be, in ſending to the diſobedient ſtrong <note n="ſ" place="margin">Saint Iohn, as it were in a map, purtrayeth the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie picture of this fooliſh worlde made ſtarke mad by the ſtrength of this deluſion. and he ſheweth it vs (as he might well do) for the great wonders of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt: for ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there be anie greater wonder, then that the inhabitants of the earth ſhould ſo generally be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deceiued? Reu. 13 verſ. 8. 12. 13. 14.</note> deluſion to beleeue lyes, 2 Theſ. 2. verſ. 10. 11. as we ſee in our obſtinate Romiſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes, whoſe conſciences are ſo caute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized (as the holy Ghoſt foretold, 1 Tim. 4. 2) that neither feare of God, obedience to their Prince, loue of their countrey, perſwaſion of friends regard of poſterity, nor care of their owne ſoules, can either diſſwade them from their damnable opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, or yet reclaime them from their deuilliſh attemptes, But of this their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible obſtinacy our Sauiour hath fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned vs, ſaying: that the time ſhould come, that whoſoeuer killeth his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples &amp; profeſſors of his word, will thinke that he doth God ſeruice, Ioh. 16, 2. Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> would ſeeme to yeeld a reaſon of this their vnreaſonable obſtinacie: they (ſaith he, ſpeaking of Antichriſtian tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers) are of the world, therefore ſpeake
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:28175:44"/> yeares, yet the holy Scripturs affirme nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the one nor the other: but rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the contrarie, Rom. 15, 20 &amp;c. Gal. 2. verſe 1. 2. 8. 9. 2 Tim. 4, 16. Yes (ſay they) in that ſalutation (The church which is at Babylon ſaluteth you, 1 Pet. 5. 13) <hi>S. Peter</hi> put Babilon for Rome. Yea what wil they not allow, ſo that they might proue that <hi>S. Peter</hi> was at Rome? But briefly, for the diſproofe of their Charter, our Lord ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing aſked his diſciples who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they thought him to be, Mat. 16, 15. <hi>Peter</hi> (as he was euer very forward in ſpeech) anſwereth in the name of the reſt: Thou art the Chriſt, the ſonne of the liuing God. Wherefore our Sauiour approuing <hi>Peters</hi> anſwer &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, being built vpon the head corner ſtone Ieſus Chriſt, Act. 4, 11. 1 Cor. 3, 11, and alluding to his name <hi>Peter,</hi> which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth a ſtone or rocke, ſaith to <hi>Peter,</hi> and in him to the reſt; for as <hi>Peter</hi> anſwered for all (for they all beleeued and confeſſed the ſame, Ioh. 6, 69) ſo all were anſwered againe in <hi>Peter:</hi> Thou art <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp; vpon this rocke (meaning, like a wiſe builder, a ſure foundation of a ſpirituall building, Mat. 7, 24. 1 Cor. 10. 4. &amp; not, as thoſe foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:28175:44"/> dawbers, Ezech. 13, 10 &amp;c. vpon the flitting ſands, Mat, 7, 26) will I build my Church, againſt which no ſtrength of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than ſhall preuaile. By the keyes is meant authoritie and power, Iſa. 22, 22. Reu. 3, 7. And here marke well the wordes of their pretenced charter: Chriſt ſaith, I wil giue vnto thee the keyes &amp;c. he ſaith not, I do giue: for notwithſtanding this true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of <hi>Peter, Peters</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Peter was then as vnſit to receiue the keyes, as he was vnable at Chriſts paſſion to followe Chriſt in ſufferings, which thing yet after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he muſt do. Ioh. 13, 36. and 21, 19. 2 Pet. 1, 14.</note> vnfitneſſe then to receiue the keyes was ſuch, that within foure verſes after in the ſame Chapter, Chriſtes verie next wordes to <hi>Peter</hi> are theſe: Get thee behind me Sathan: Thou art an offence vnto me, becauſe thou vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſt not the things that are of God, but the things that are of men, Mat. 16, 23. And <hi>Peter</hi> only of al the Apoſtles, a good ſpace after this, denied with an oth, &amp; that at the inſtance of a ſilly gerle, that euer he had any acquaintance with Chriſt, Mat. 26, 74. we ſee therfore that thogh they wil haue here their Charter ingroſt, yet was it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neither deliuered, nor vnder ſeale: but both were don after Chriſts reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; at the time of ſealing &amp; deliuering, Chriſt deliuered theſe keys of binding &amp; looſing
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:28175:45"/> ſinnes, aſwel to all the other Diſciples, as to <hi>S. Peter,</hi> Ioh. 20. verſ. 22. 23. As likewiſe they haue euer bene in the church of God Iude ver. 14. 2 Pet. 2, 7. Ier. 1, 10. And <note n="z" place="margin">There are then no keyes for the pope, but that one keye of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe pit. Reu. 9, 1 &amp;c.</note> are in all the iuſt miniſters of Gods word, &amp; alway ſhalbe, Mat. 18. verſe 17. 18. 1 Cor. 5, 4 &amp;c. 2 Cor. 2. verſe 7. 15. and 10, 4. 1. Tim. 5. verſe 20. 24. Iud. verſ. 22. 23. Yea, though their priuiledge were good (as we ſee it counterfet and common) yet muſt it ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be perſonal, or locall, or mixt of both. If it be perſonal, it periſhed with <hi>Peter:</hi> if locall, what place ſhall euer be of ſo great priuiledge &amp; prerogatiues, as was mount Sion, Ieruſalem? what ſpecial couenants?<note place="margin">Sions preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues.</note> what excellent promiſes had ſhe? <q>God hath layd his foundations among the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mountaines: the Lord loued the gates of Sion aboue all the habitations of <hi>Iacob.</hi> Of Sion it ſhall be ſaid, many are borne in her, and the Moſt-high ſhall ſtabliſh her &amp;c. Pſal. 87, 1 &amp;c. For the Lord hath choſen Sion, and loued to dwell in it, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: This is my reſt for euer, here will I dwell,</q> for I haue a delight therein, &amp;c. Pſal. 132, 13 &amp;c. And the Iewes were not a litle proud hereof, Ier. 7, 3 &amp;c. but Gods
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:28175:45"/> promiſes to Ieruſalem were conditionall: if thy ſonnes keepe my couenant &amp;c. Pſa. 132, 12. for elſe it ſhould be ſerued as Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo was, Ierem. 7, 14. Ieruſalem ſhould be counted as Sodome, Ezech. 16. verſe 48. 53.<note place="margin">Reade 2 King. 23, 27.</note> and Sion for their ſake, ſhould be plowed as a field, and Ieruſalem become as heaps, Micah 3, 12. And touching local worſhip, our Sauiour hath taught vs in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication to the woman of Samaria, that the true worſhippers of God ſhould looke for none, Ioh. 4. verſe 20. 21. 23. for men may, and muſt, pray in euery place, liſting vp pure hands without wrath and <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 21. verſe 21 22. Iames 1, 6.</note> doubting, 1 Tim. 2, 8. 1 Cor. 1, 2. To come then to their Church, how is their church the Church of Chriſt, ſeeing they reiect the word of God, as they do? Our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our reaſoneth thus againſt the Iewes: He that is of God, heareth Gods wordes, ye therefore heare them not, becauſe ye are not of God, Ioh. 8, 47. If all men be bound to allow this reaſon (as vpon pain of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation they are) howe is the Church of <note n="a" place="margin">This is meant of their viſible &amp; out ward Church, for elſe there are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them many (no doubt) who fearing God and embracing his word, abhorre the Beaſt, &amp; deteſt his religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as were in that corrupt time of Ahab, 1 king. 19 ver. 10. 18. Rom. 11 ver. 3. 4. And good Obadia, a chiefe officer in Ahabs Court, 1 king. 18, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and in S. Paules time, they of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros houſhold at Rome, Phil. 4, 22.</note> Rome a member of the Church of God, ſith it refuſeth to heare his woord? as wee ſee by practiſe in their
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:28175:46"/>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Recuſants are to bee compelled to come &amp; heare the word of God, Lu. 14, 23. by theſe examples, Ioſh. 24 23 &amp;c. 2 Chro. 34, 33. Ezra 7, 26. Ne. 10. ve. 1. 28 &amp;c. And by theſe warrants, Exod. 22, 20. Nom. 9, 13. Deut. 13, 12 &amp;c. &amp; 17, 2 &amp;c. Iſa 8, 20. Zec. 13, 2 &amp;c. for like as by their refuſing to heare Gods word, they ſhew them ſelues not to be of God, as our Lord teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth Ioh. 8, 47: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo, through the ſame refuſall, their prayer and diuine ſeruice is abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in Gods ſight, as the holy Ghoſt witneſſeth, Prou. 28, 9. And euen to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the liuing God otherwiſe then he preſcribeth in his word, is all one thing vnto him, as to ſerue Idoles, and ſtrange gods onely, as we may ſee, Exod. 32. ve. 1. 4 &amp;c. and 1 king. 12, 28. and 2 king. 17. verſe 28. 29. 32 &amp;c. where thoſe calfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhippers, in ſhew of the Calfe, pretended the worſhip of the true God, as plainly appeareth by Aarons Holy-day to the Lord, Exod. 32, 5. and by Ierobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams craftie tendering the peoples farre iourneyes to worſhip God at Ieruſalem 1 king. 12, 28. Alſo in Ezech. 43. verſe 7. 8. and Zephan. 1, 5. they mingled their image-worſhip with Gods ſeruice. And therefore Act. 7. verſe 43. 44. Gods Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle is called the Tabernacle of Moloch, becauſe the Iewes in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe worſhipped God with Moloch, the Idoll of the Ammonites, Leuit. 20, 2 &amp;c. Amos 5, 25. for what agreement hath the Temple of God with Idoles? 2 Cor. 6, 16. And becauſe our Recuſants are Idolaters, and Image-ſeruers, and therefore can ſpiritually neither ſee, nor vnderſtand, as the holy Ghoſt teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, Iſa. 44, 18. Pſalm. 115, 8. 2 Theſ. 2, 10 &amp;c. they are the more to be conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and pitied by compulſion, 2 Tim. 2. verſe 25. 26. Iude verſe 23.</note> Recuſants, &amp; in other open contempts. Which thing doubtleſſe they do, becauſe the word is not marked with the marke, name and image of their Beaſt, and, the number, and print of his name, Reuel. 13. verſe 16. 17. and 14, 11. which is, to be read in Latin: to carrie the priuate expoſition of their Church: to be mingled with the wormwoodiſh and bitter waters of their Church-traditions &amp;c. Reu. 8, 10 &amp;c. And becauſe alſo that they take their Church to be aboue Gods word: for the holie Scriptures lie vnder the checke (forſooth) of their Church. But the word of God ſhall iudge them in the laſt day, Ioh. 12, 48. dare they then controll their iudge? Exo.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:28175:46"/> 22, 28. Againe, how may their Church o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer rule the holy Scripturs, ſith it is Gods word that muſt either approue it the Church of Chriſt, or conuince it the ſyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of Satan? Ioh. 7, 17. Rom. 6, 17. 1 Io. 4, 1. 2 Ioh, verſe 10. And we haue ſeene, in the beginning of this Treatiſe, that the time was, and that ſince mans Creation, when there was no Church at all. <hi>viz.</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> being Satans bondſlaues, were hid in the buſhes: and til they heard the word of the promiſe of redemption, they were no members of Gods Church. But by faith onely in that word of God, they were regenerate into the Church of Chriſt, as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh, 1 Pet. 1, 23 Therefore the doctrine of the Catholikes is moſt abſurd to teach that the Church, being begotten by the immortall ſeed of Gods word, may after dare (like a mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert impe) to controll, or infringe the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of that word, and to preſume to ouer rule it. But we ſillie ſoules cannot ſee that their <note n="b" place="margin">The Papiſts pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend Chriſts pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe for this ſpirit, Ioh. 14, 26 but our Lord promiſeth, that the holy Ghoſt ſhould ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt onely that, which himſelf had taught (reade the place) now Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught nothing but out of the law and the Prophets, Luk. 24, 44. Act. 26 22. Therfore their ſpirit teaching o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, is a coſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning counterfet.</note> priui-pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt-ſpirit inſtructeth their Church of higher, and more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent things, then the holy Scriptures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouch: among which (I trowe) are theſe:
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:28175:47"/> That their Pope cannot erre: That the Virgine <hi>Marie,</hi> and Saints departed this life, muſt be prayed vnto: That images (not Idoles) muſt be worſhipped, That a Catholike is not bound to keepe faith, &amp; truce with an hereticke (for ſo it pleaſeth them to cal the profeſſors of Gods word) &amp;c. which abſurd aſſertions, &amp; all other their priuate doctrines taught vnder the title of that ſpirit, by the authority of their church, they hold and maintaine with no better reaſon, or more ſure ground, then the Iewes do the Traditions of their <note n="c" place="margin">Cabal is the I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wes myſticall doctrin, deliuered from one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by tradition, which (as they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme) was not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to writing, as was Gods Law: but deliuered by Moſes to their forefathers by word of mouth.</note> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal, or Mahomet the ceremonies of his <note n="d" place="margin">Alcoran is a booke containing the law, &amp; religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Mahomet, with out the knowlege wherof the Turks teach that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are but childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning religion.</note> Alcoran. And as it were hard for man to deeme which of theſe three abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions haue ſent mo millions of ſoules to hell-fire: ſo were it as vneth to ſay, which of the three be more hatefull in Gods ſight, were it not that the Pope hath grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter light to his heauier iudgement at the laſt day. And when our Papiſts, maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning theſe, and more groſſe opinions, and croſſing the word of God, be the true me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſtes Church: then ſhall thoſe Iewes be the children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who yet bare no reſemblance of <hi>Abrahams</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:28175:47"/> faith, and therefore our Lord told them, that they were of their father the Deuill, Ioh. 8. verſe 39. 44. Wherefore we wil end with this fearefull Caueat to them all,<note place="margin">A Caueat to the Catholikes.</note> That the ſtate of a reſolute and perfect Papiſt, not repenting his religion, but dying ſo inſected and poſſeſſed with the poyſon of Papiſtrie, is vndoubtedly a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led caſe in the holy Scriptures, and ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth damnable by their cenſure, as theſe, and ſuch like places of the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t giue manifeſt euidence, 2 Theſ. 2, 3 &amp;c. 1 Tim 4, 1 &amp;c. 2 Tim. 3, 1 &amp;c. 2 Pet. 2, 1 &amp;c. Reu. 13, 8. &amp; 14. verſe 9. 10. &amp; 15, 2. &amp; 20. verſe 4. 5. Seeing then their caſe is ſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous, let vs heare once againe the triple teſtimonie of Gods ſpirit thus mercifully<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5, 7.</note> forewarning vs: Be not therfore compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions with them. Turne away therefore<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3, 5.</note> from ſuch. And, by a voice from heauen: Go out of her, my people, that ye be not<note place="margin">Reuel. 18, 4.</note> partakers in her ſinnes, and that ye receiue not of her plagues.</p>
            <closer>Amen. He that hath eares to heare let him heare, Pro. 20, 12. Ezech. 12, 2. Mat. 11, 15.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:28175:48"/>
            <head>A TABLE SHEVVING THE PRINCIPAL THINGS contained in this Treatiſe, wherein the figures declare the page, and where you finde a letter after anie figure, there in the marginal note vnder the ſame letter is handled the matter you ſeeke for.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A</head>
               <item>Aarons holy-day. 84. a</item>
               <item>Abaddon. 63. and 66. q</item>
               <item>Abraham borne. 7. Called from Vr, anno mundi 2079. 19. ſaw the dayes of Chriſt, 13. by three proofes his faith is ſpecially commended. 8. m. In him all the families of the earth are bleſſed. 8. The Lords coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with him. 51. and 52.</item>
               <item>Adam created the ſixt day of the weeke. 2. that day alſo being our Friday, is ſuppoſed the day of his tranſgreſſion and redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 2. b.</item>
               <item>Adams perfection and royaltie in his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie. 2. his tranſgreſſion a moſt haynous ſinne. 3. f. huy-and-cry after Adam. 4. his examination. ibid. his faith in the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſeed Chriſt. 4. his exerciſes of faith. 5 his robes. 5. h. his ſonnes ſacrifices. 5</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:28175:48"/>
               <item>ſpirituall Adulterie. 42</item>
               <item>Mahomets Alcoran. 86</item>
               <item>Angels created when, and wherfore. 1. a. their deſire to ſee the glorie of the elect. 71</item>
               <item>The Angels not able to behold Gods ful ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie. 72</item>
               <item>Antiehriſt ſitteth in the temple of God. 64. n. his power. 79. x. his liuerie. 64. o. his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. 77. ſ. Two ſpeciall notes of him. 32.</item>
               <item>Apollyon. 63</item>
               <item>Bildads Argument againſt Iob. 51</item>
               <item>Ar-mageddon. 66</item>
               <item>Aſia minor. 63. m.</item>
               <item>the Authoritie of the Scriptures. 28. which the Papiſtes blaſphemouſly miſcall, and why. 60</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B</head>
               <item>Babylon built. 61. k. cruelly captiueth and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicteth Gods Church the Iewes. 62. their deliuerance from thence. 19</item>
               <item>the Babylonians deſtroy Gods Temple, and their reward therefore. 61. ſo do the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes. 62</item>
               <item>Rome is Babylon. 62. and 80.</item>
               <item>a faire beginning of Babylons foyle. 66</item>
               <item>Caiaphas ſpeaketh like Balams aſſe. 21. u.</item>
               <item>Barak. 67</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:28175:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>Baptiſme repreſenteth our mortification. 45</item>
               <item>the Beaſtes characterie name. 63</item>
               <item>Chriſt among wild Beaſts. 40</item>
               <item>Chriſts Bodie taken from the croſſe. 21</item>
               <item>the glorious exchange of our Bodies. 71</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C</head>
               <item>The Iewes Cabal. 86</item>
               <item>Caiaphas prophecieth and blaſphemeth with one voyce. 21. u.</item>
               <item>Abraham <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alled out of Chaldea. 8. and 19</item>
               <item>Catholikes obſtinate, and why. 77. their filthy cage Rome. 61. their charter. 79. a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full caueat to them. 87.</item>
               <item>the whole courſe of nature Curſed. 4. g. na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures deſire. 71</item>
               <item>Chriſt the bleſſed ſeede. 5. his natiuitie. 14. his baptiſme. 37. his priuate life. 36<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his two natures. 11. q. how we obtaine his righteouſneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 24. his skarlet robe. 64. o. he is our king, high prieſt and Prophet. 34. he onely heareth our prayers. 24. the yeare of his paſſion foretold. 20. his aſcenſion. 14. his ſecond comming. 69. q. his manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the world, like to the appearance of the Sunnes ariſing. 16</item>
               <item>Chriſt crucified from the beginning of the world. 5. viſibly repleniſhed with the holy
<pb facs="tcp:28175:49" rendition="simple:additions"/> Ghoſt. 40. he is the onely perfection of Chriſtians. 24. and 40 &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Chriſtians apparell. 5. h. why they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce. 74. their aſſured hope of eternal life. ibid. their inheritance not in their owne keeping. 69. as was Adams. 3. how they ſhould examine them ſelues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 69. r.</item>
               <item>three notable deliuerances of Gods Church, and all at one time of the yeare. 19</item>
               <item>why the preſent Church of Rome is no church of Chriſt. 83</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>The Day by the Iewes account. 20</item>
               <item>a Day for a yeare. 20</item>
               <item>Babylons great Day. 66</item>
               <item>how Dauid ſaw Chriſt crucified. 13</item>
               <item>Deaths entrance and power by ſinne. 2. d</item>
               <item>all Dead in Adam. 2. d. and 47</item>
               <item>Deboras ſong. 67</item>
               <item>Deuilliſh ſpirits. 66</item>
               <item>Antichriſtian Doctrine carnall. 78</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>Eating of fleſh &amp; fiſh when firſt permitted. 6. k</item>
               <item>Gods Church deliuered from Egypt. 19</item>
               <item>Rome called Egypt, and why. 62</item>
               <item>Elias ſlayeth Baals Prophets. 67</item>
               <item>the Iewes generall Error, that Elias ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:28175:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> come againe. 22</item>
               <item>our ſpirituall Enemies. 47. conquered by Chriſt. 15. r. 53. and 54.</item>
               <item>the time of the Iewes euening prayer and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. 20. and 21</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>Moſes bright Face. 71. and 72</item>
               <item>by Faith in Chriſt were all the Patriarkes ſaued. 4</item>
               <item>the ten Fathers before the flood. 6</item>
               <item>two kindes of Feare. 45. c</item>
               <item>the Firſt borne were ſacrificers before the law. 5 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Fleſh permitted to be eaten. 6. k</item>
               <item>Noahs Flood what yere, 5. month &amp; day, 7. k</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G</head>
               <item>Gabriels miniſterie in the meſſage of Chriſts humanitie. 20</item>
               <item>the Gentiles gathered into the ſheep-fold of the Iewes. 9. o</item>
               <item>Gideon. 55</item>
               <item>God alloweth nothing but what himſelf com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth. 76</item>
               <item>the true marke of the Godly in all ages. 69. q.</item>
               <item>Goliath. 53</item>
               <item>Good and ill angell. 22. t</item>
               <item>Good workes, and their right vſe. 44. and 47</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:28175:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>Grace and thankeſgiuing at meate vſed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Lawe. 32. a</item>
               <item>the Great citie. 65</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H</head>
               <item>Onely Chriſt Heareth our prayers. 24</item>
               <item>Heathen who they were. 7. l. and 9. gathered into the ſheepefold of the Iewes. 9. o. their prophane opinions receiued of the Iewes. 22. t. their Diuines. 49</item>
               <item>a deſcription of the Heauenly Ieruſalem. 70</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>Iabin king of Canaan. 67</item>
               <item>Iacob. 6. his prophecie of Chriſts birth. 22</item>
               <item>Iapheth perſwaded to dwell in the tentes of Sem. 63. m</item>
               <item>Idolatrie. 42. and 79</item>
               <item>Idole and Image differ not. 79. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Ieroboams craftie pollicie. 84. a</item>
               <item>heauenly Ieruſalem. 70</item>
               <item>Ieruſalem a ſpectacle of peace in the middest of the nations. 23. x</item>
               <item>the Iewes ſeparation fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Gentiles when, and how long. 8. 9. and 48</item>
               <item>ſome Iewes waited for Chriſts coming. 21. u</item>
               <item>the Iewes receiued the prophane opinions of the heathen. 22. t</item>
               <item>the Iewes captiued by the Babylonians when. 61 k.
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:28175:51"/>
               <item>their charter examined, 80. and 81. when it was ſealed. 81. their prompt-ſpirit. 85. b a heauie caueat to them. 87</item>
               <item>Paradiſe. 2</item>
               <item>the Iewes vaine confidence of peace. 23. x</item>
               <item>S. Peter neuer at Rome. 79. x. and 80. his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle. 72. he vnfit for the keyes. 81. y. Chriſt calleth him Satan. ibid.</item>
               <item>Phariſies ſet non-plus. 11. q</item>
               <item>S. Iohns Picture of this world. 77. ſ.</item>
               <item>Pilate the Romane Deputie. 62</item>
               <item>Rome the Place where our Lord was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. ibid.</item>
               <item>Poets and Philoſophers diuines of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. 49</item>
               <item>Poperie a late vpſtart. 30. no point thereof in Scripture. 48</item>
               <item>the Pope in Christes skarlet robe. 64. o. they ſay he cannot erre. 86. his keyes. 82. z. he is Antichriſt. 63. and 78. he ſitteth in the temple of God. 64. n. he is the coſoner of the coſoner of the world. 60. &amp; 79. w. he made ill choiſe of Peter. 79. x</item>
               <item>Preaching. 26. the efficacie thereof. 56. e.</item>
               <item>Prickes Hebrew vowels when inuented. 59. h.</item>
               <item>all Gods promiſes ratified in Chriſt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed ſeede. 15</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:28175:51"/>
               <item>Prophecies of Antichrist, and notes of him. 31. and 32.</item>
               <item>Caiaphas Prophecieth of Chriſts death. 21. u</item>
               <item>Purgatorie Papiſticall. 48. and 49</item>
               <item>a double Purgatorie of Chriſtians in this life 49. and 50. &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R</head>
               <item>Reading gods word of what eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cacie. 26. &amp; 27</item>
               <item>the iuſt triall of true Religion. 29</item>
               <item>Recuſants are to be compelled to heare Gods word. 84. a</item>
               <item>why Chriſt Redeemed vs. 46</item>
               <item>Rhemiſh Catholikes. 77</item>
               <item>hovv vve attaine Chriſtes Righteouſneſſe. 24. and 25.</item>
               <item>our Riſing againe to a nevvneſſe of life re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in Baptiſme. 45. and 46</item>
               <item>Rome. 61. it is called Babylon, Sodome, Egypt, the place vvhere our Lord vvas crucified, and vvhy. 62. it is alſo called an vgly cage 62. and the great citie diuided into three parts. 65. built vpon ſeuen mountaines. 63 and 64.</item>
               <item>hovv the Romanes dealt vvith Chriſt. 62</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>the Sacrifice of Chriſtes bodie ſufficient for all: but effectual only for the elect. 35. &amp; 36</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:28175:52"/>
               <item>what Sacrifices meant. 5. h. and 11. how they were approued. 5. i. their right vſe. 11</item>
               <item>the Sacrifices of Chriſtians. 36. and 52</item>
               <item>our Saluation onely in Chriſt. 23. and 24</item>
               <item>a Similitude of our vnableneſſe in our ſelues to helpe Gods graces in the worke of our Saluation. 46. d</item>
               <item>to kill Gods Saints thought Gods ſeruice. 77</item>
               <item>why Moſes deſcribeth Satan vnder the name of a ſerpent. 3. e</item>
               <item>Satan vnlooſed. 31</item>
               <item>The Scepter departed from Iudah. 22</item>
               <item>the ſeede of the woman ſhall bruſe the ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts head. 4. what it meaneth. 15. &amp; 18. the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of that ſeed renued in diuerſe ages. 7. 9. &amp; 11. the law a plat-forme of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed ſeed. 10</item>
               <item>Sems generation. 7. and 14</item>
               <item>the holy Scriptures. 28. ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therin bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth error. 76. they are our guide. 29. they are blaſphemed by the papiſts. 60. they are ſufficient to ſaluation. 28. the Iewes falſly charged to corrupt them. 58</item>
               <item>the power of Sinne. 2. d</item>
               <item>Sions prerogatiues. 82</item>
               <item>Siſera. 67</item>
               <item>Adam clothed in beaſts skinnes. 5. h</item>
               <item>the Soule of man, diuine and immortall. 2. c</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:28175:52"/>
               <item>Spirituall adulterie. 42</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T</head>
               <item>Peters Tabernacle. 72</item>
               <item>Gods Temple and citie deſtroyed, firſt by the Babylonians, 61. after by the Romanes. 62 which Chriſt aduiſeth vs to conſider. 62. l</item>
               <item>the Tents of the Saints. 66</item>
               <item>the whole doctrine of the new Teſtament con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the old. 59</item>
               <item>Time when it began. 1. a</item>
               <item>Adams Tranſgreſſion a moſt hainous ſin. 3. f</item>
               <item>we muſt al appear before chriſts tribunal. 76</item>
               <item>the holy Trinitie. 1. and 73</item>
               <item>Types of the promiſed ſeed. 5</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V</head>
               <item>Vaine words, &amp; the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t therof. 76. 77.</item>
               <item>Vain worſhipping of god by doctrins of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 76</item>
               <item>the Virgine Marie no mediatreſſe. 30. &amp; 33</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W</head>
               <item>Our ſpirituall warfare. 53</item>
               <item>the Weapons wherwith Chriſt ouercame Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. 15. r. &amp; 53. vvhich all Chriſtians are commanded to put on. 15. r. they are not carnall. 56</item>
               <item>the Wedding garment. 5. h</item>
               <item>Why Chriſt Wept ouer Ieruſalem. 21</item>
               <item>the Wicked in the old vvorld toke no notice of the floods comming. 7</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:28175:53"/>
               <item>Gods Word is our life. 29. and the onely ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thereof. 76. it ſhall be our iudge. 84. vvh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Recuſants refuſe to herre it. 84. Paule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reaſon to hold vs thereto onely. 29. and 30<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vvhat dare controll it. 84<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </item>
               <item>Workes. 44. and their right vſe. 46. and 47</item>
               <item>to Worke the vvorke of God. 78. t</item>
               <item>calfe-Worſhip. 84. a</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults eſcaped in the printing.</head>
            <p>Page 2. of the Epiſtle, lin. 19. for vnſeaſonable read vnſeaſoned. pag. 5. in the note i, for as the law. r. at the law. p. 15. l. 26. compoundeth. r. expoundeth. p. 16. l. 6. the r. that. p. 19. in the marge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. 2709. r. 2079. p. 30. l. 14. childred. r. children. p. 39. l. 7. for the full point before was. wrire the later braſe of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentheſis begun p. 38. l. 8. p. 56. l. 25. ordinance. r. obedience. p. 59. l. 7. little. r. tittle.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:28175:53"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
